<div3 id="elem.3.35" n="35" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 35.</head>
      <p><emph>If in a circle two straight lines cut one another</emph>, <emph>the rectangle contained by the segments of the one is equal to the rectangle contained by the segments of the other</emph>. </p>
      <p>For in the circle <emph>ABCD</emph> let the two straight lines <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>BD</emph> cut one another at the point <emph>E</emph>; I say that the rectangle contained by <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> is equal to the rectangle contained by <emph>DE</emph>, <emph>EB</emph>. </p>
      <p>If now <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>BD</emph> are through the centre, so that <emph>E</emph> is the centre of the circle <emph>ABCD</emph>, it is manifest that, <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph>, <emph>DE</emph>, <emph>EB</emph> being equal, the rectangle contained by <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> is also equal to the rectangle contained by <emph>DE</emph>, <emph>EB</emph>. </p>
      <p>Next let <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>DB</emph> not be through the centre; let the centre of <emph>ABCD</emph> be taken, and let it be <emph>F</emph>; from <emph>F</emph> let <emph>FG</emph>, <emph>FH</emph> be drawn perpendicular to the straight lines <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>DB</emph>, and let <emph>FB</emph>, <emph>FC</emph>, <emph>FE</emph> be joined. </p>
      <p>Then, since a straight line <emph>GF</emph> through the centre cuts a straight line <emph>AC</emph> not through the centre at right angles, <hi rend="center">it also bisects it; [<ref target="elem.3.3" targOrder="U">III. 3</ref>] therefore <emph>AG</emph> is equal to <emph>GC</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Since, then, the straight line <emph>AC</emph> has been cut into equal parts at <emph>G</emph> and into unequal parts at <emph>E</emph>, the rectangle contained by <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> together with the square on <emph>EG</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>GC</emph>; [<ref target="elem.2.5" targOrder="U">II. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let the square on <emph>GF</emph> be added; therefore the rectangle <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> together with the squares on <emph>GE</emph>, <emph>GF</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>CG</emph>, <emph>GF</emph>. </p>
      <p>But the square on <emph>FE</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>EG</emph>, <emph>GF</emph>, and the square on <emph>FC</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>CG</emph>, <emph>GF</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.47" targOrder="U">I. 47</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore the rectangle <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> together with the square on <emph>FE</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>FC</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And <emph>FC</emph> is equal to <emph>FB</emph>; therefore the rectangle <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> together with the square on <emph>EF</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>FB</emph>. </p>
      <p>For the same reason, also, the rectangle <emph>DE</emph>, <emph>EB</emph> together with the square on <emph>FE</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>FB</emph>. </p>
      <p>But the rectangle <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> together with the square on <emph>FE</emph> was also proved equal to the square on <emph>FB</emph>; therefore the rectangle <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> together with the square on <emph>FE</emph> is equal to the rectangle <emph>DE</emph>, <emph>EB</emph> together with the square on <emph>FE</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let the square on <emph>FE</emph> be subtracted from each; therefore the rectangle contained by <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> which remains is equal to the rectangle contained by <emph>DE</emph>, <emph>EB</emph>. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc.</p>
     </div3>
     
