<div3 id="elem.6.28" n="28" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 28.</head>
      <p><emph>To a given straight line to apply a parallelogram equal to a given rectilineal figure and deficient by a parallelogrammic figure similar to a given one : thus the given rectilineal figure must not be greater than the parallelogram described on the half of the straight line and similar to the defect</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>AB</emph> be the given straight line, <emph>C</emph> the given rectilineal figure to which the figure to be applied to <emph>AB</emph> is required to be equal, not being greater than the parallelogram described on the half of <emph>AB</emph> and similar to the defect, and <emph>D</emph> the parallelogram to which the defect is required to be similar; <emph>AB</emph> a parallelogram equal to the given rectilineal figure <emph>C</emph> and deficient by a parallelogrammic figure which is similar to <emph>D</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>AB</emph> be bisected at the point <emph>E</emph>, and on <emph>EB</emph> let <emph>EBFG</emph> be described similar and similarly situated to <emph>D</emph>; [<ref target="elem.6.18" targOrder="U">VI. 18</ref>] let the parallelogram <emph>AG</emph> be completed. </p>
      <p>If then <emph>AG</emph> is equal to <emph>C</emph>, that which was enjoined will have been done; <hi rend="center">for there has been applied to the given straight line <emph>AB</emph> the parallelogram <emph>AG</emph> equal to the given rectilineal figure <emph>C</emph> and deficient by a parallelogrammic figure <emph>GB</emph> which is similar to <emph>D</emph>.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>But, if not, let <emph>HE</emph> be greater than <emph>C</emph>. </p>
      <p>Now <emph>HE</emph> is equal to <emph>GB</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>GB</emph> is also greater than <emph>C</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <emph>KLMN</emph> be constructed at once equal to the excess by which <emph>GB</emph> is greater than <emph>C</emph> and similar and similarly situated to <emph>D</emph>. [<ref target="elem.6.25" targOrder="U">VI. 25</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <emph>D</emph> is similar to <emph>GB</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>KM</emph> is also similar to <emph>GB</emph>. [<ref target="elem.6.21" targOrder="U">VI. 21</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let, then, <emph>KL</emph> correspond to <emph>GE</emph>, and <emph>LM</emph> to <emph>GF</emph>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <emph>GB</emph> is equal to <emph>C</emph>, <emph>KM</emph>, <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>GB</emph> is greater than <emph>KM</emph>; therefore also <emph>GE</emph> is greater than <emph>KL</emph>, and <emph>GF</emph> than <emph>LM</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <emph>GO</emph> be made equal to <emph>KL</emph>, and <emph>GP</emph> equal to <emph>LM</emph>; and let the parallelogram <emph>OGPQ</emph> be completed; <hi rend="center">therefore it is equal and similar to <emph>KM</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore <emph>GQ</emph> is also similar to <emph>GB</emph>; [<ref target="elem.6.21" targOrder="U">VI. 21</ref>] therefore <emph>GQ</emph> is about the same diameter with <emph>GB</emph>. [<ref target="elem.6.26" targOrder="U">VI. 26</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let <emph>GQB</emph> be their diameter, and let the figure be described. </p>
      <p>Then, since <emph>BG</emph> is equal to <emph>C</emph>, <emph>KM</emph>, and in them <emph>GQ</emph> is equal to <emph>KM</emph>, therefore the remainder, the gnomon <emph>UWV</emph>, is equal to the remainder <emph>C</emph>. </p>
      <p>And, since <emph>PR</emph> is equal to <emph>OS</emph>, <hi rend="center">let <emph>QB</emph> be added to each;</hi> therefore the whole <emph>PB</emph> is equal to the whole <emph>OB</emph>. </p>
      <p>But <emph>OB</emph> is equal to <emph>TE</emph>, since the side <emph>AE</emph> is also equal to the side <emph>EB</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.36" targOrder="U">I. 36</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>TE</emph> is also equal to <emph>PB</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <emph>OS</emph> be added to each; <hi rend="center">therefore the whole <emph>TS</emph> is equal to the whole, the gnomon <emph>VWU</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But the gnomon <emph>VWU</emph> was proved equal to <emph>C</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>TS</emph> is also equal to <emph>C</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore to the given straight line <emph>AB</emph> there has been applied the parallelogram <emph>ST</emph> equal to the given rectilineal figure <emph>C</emph> and deficient by a parallelogrammic figure <emph>QB</emph> which is similar to <emph>D</emph>. Q. E. F.</p>
     </div3>
     
