<div3 id="elem.6.29" n="29" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 29.</head>
      <p><emph>To a given straight line to apply a parallelogram equal to a given rectilineal figure and exceeding by a parallelogrammic figure similar to a given one</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>AB</emph> be the given straight line, <emph>C</emph> the given rectilineal figure to which the figure to be applied to <emph>AB</emph> is required to be equal, and <emph>D</emph> that to which the excess is required to be similar; thus it is required to apply to the straight line <emph>AB</emph> a parallelogram equal to the rectilineal figure <emph>C</emph> and exceeding by a parallelogrammic figure similar to <emph>D</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>AB</emph> be bisected at <emph>E</emph>; let there be described on <emph>EB</emph> the parallelogram <emph>BF</emph> similar and similarly situated to <emph>D</emph>; and let <emph>GH</emph> be constructed at once equal to the sum of <emph>BF</emph>, <emph>C</emph> and similar and similarly situated to <emph>D</emph>. [<ref target="elem.6.25" targOrder="U">VI. 25</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let <emph>KH</emph> correspond to <emph>FL</emph> and <emph>KG</emph> to <emph>FE</emph>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <emph>GH</emph> is greater than <emph>FB</emph>, therefore <emph>KH</emph> is also greater than <emph>FL</emph>, and <emph>KG</emph> than <emph>FE</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>FL</emph>, <emph>FE</emph> be produced, let <emph>FLM</emph> be equal to <emph>KH</emph>, and <emph>FEN</emph> to <emph>KG</emph>, and let <emph>MN</emph> be completed; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>MN</emph> is both equal and similar to <emph>GH</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But <emph>GH</emph> is similar to <emph>EL</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>MN</emph> is also similar to <emph>EL</emph>; [<ref target="elem.6.21" targOrder="U">VI. 21</ref>]</hi> therefore <emph>EL</emph> is about the same diameter with <emph>MN</emph>. [<ref target="elem.6.26" targOrder="U">VI. 26</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let their diameter <emph>FO</emph> be drawn, and let the figure be described. </p>
      <p>Since <emph>GH</emph> is equal to <emph>EL</emph>, <emph>C</emph>, while <emph>GH</emph> is equal to <emph>MN</emph>, therefore <emph>MN</emph> is also equal to <emph>EL</emph>, <emph>C</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>EL</emph> be subtracted from each; <hi rend="center">therefore the remainder, the gnomon <emph>XWV</emph>, is equal to <emph>C</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Now, since <emph>AE</emph> is equal to <emph>EB</emph>, <hi rend="center"><emph>AN</emph> is also equal to <emph>NB</emph> [<ref target="elem.1.36" targOrder="U">I. 36</ref>], that is, to <emph>LP</emph> [<ref target="elem.1.43" targOrder="U">I. 43</ref>].</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <emph>EO</emph> be added to each; <hi rend="center">therefore the whole <emph>AO</emph> is equal to the gnomon <emph>VWX</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But the gnomon <emph>VWX</emph> is equal to <emph>C</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>AO</emph> is also equal to <emph>C</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore to the given straight line <emph>AB</emph> there has been applied the parallelogram <emph>AO</emph> equal to the given rectilineal figure <emph>C</emph> and exceeding by a parallelogrammic figure <emph>QP</emph> which is similar to <emph>D</emph>, since <emph>PQ</emph> is also similar to <emph>EL</emph> [<ref target="elem.6.24" targOrder="U">VI. 24</ref>]. Q. E. F.</p>
     </div3>
     
