<div3 id="elem.10.87" n="87" type="propositions 85&#x2014;115">
      <head>PROPOSITION 87.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">To find the third apotome</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let a rational straight line <hi rend="ital">A</hi> be set out, let three numbers <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> be set out which have not to one another the ratio which a square number has to a square number, but let <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> have to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number. </p>
      <p>Let it be contrived that, as <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.6.p.1" targOrder="U">X. 6, Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>Since then, as <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.6" targOrder="U">X. 6</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is rational; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is also rational; therefore <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is rational. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">E</hi> has not to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number, therefore neither has the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] </p>
      <p>Again, since, as <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.6" targOrder="U">X. 6</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is rational; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> is also rational; therefore <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> is rational. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has not to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number, therefore neither has the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] </p>
      <p>And both are rational; therefore <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> is an apotome. [<ref target="elem.10.73" targOrder="U">X. 73</ref>] </p>
      <p>I say next that it is also a third apotome. </p>
      <p>For since, as <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, and, as <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>, therefore, <hi rend="ital">ex aequali</hi>, as <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.22" targOrder="U">V. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">E</hi> has not to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore neither has the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore neither of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">A</hi> set out. </p>
      <p>Now let the square on <hi rend="ital">K</hi> be that by which the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. </p>
      <p>Since then, as <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, therefore, <foreign lang="la">convertendo</foreign>, as <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">K</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.19.p.1" targOrder="U">V. 19, Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> also has to the square on <hi rend="ital">K</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">K</hi>, [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] and the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. </p>
      <p>And neither of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">A</hi> set out; therefore <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> is a third apotome. [<ref target="elem.10.def.3.3" targOrder="U">X. Deff. III. 3</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore the third apotome <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> has been found. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
