<div3 id="elem.2.4" n="4" type="proposition">
      <head>Proposition 4.</head>
      <p><emph>If a straight line be cut at random</emph>, <emph>the square on the whole is equal to the squares on the segments and twice the rectangle contained by the segments</emph>.</p>
      <p>For let the straight line <emph>AB</emph> be cut at random at <emph>C</emph>; <emph>AB</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph> and twice the rectangle contained by <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph>.</p>
      <p>For let the square <emph>ADEB</emph> be described on <emph>AB</emph>, [<ref target="elem.1.46" targOrder="U">I. 46</ref>] <emph>BD</emph> be joined; through <emph>C</emph> let <emph>CF</emph> be drawn parallel to either <emph>AD</emph> or <emph>EB</emph>, and through <emph>G</emph> let <emph>HK</emph> be drawn parallel to either <emph>AB</emph> or <emph>DE</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.31" targOrder="U">I. 31</ref>] </p>
      <p>Then, since <emph>CF</emph> is parallel to <emph>AD</emph>, and <emph>BD</emph> has fallen on them, the exterior angle <emph>CGB</emph> is equal to the interior and opposite angle <emph>ADB</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.29" targOrder="U">I. 29</ref>]</p>
      <p>But the angle <emph>ADB</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>ABD</emph>, <hi rend="center">since the side <emph>BA</emph> is also equal to <emph>AD</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.5" targOrder="U">I. 5</ref>]</hi> therefore the angle <emph>CGB</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>GBC</emph>, so that the side <emph>BC</emph> is also equal to the side <emph>CG</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.6" targOrder="U">I. 6</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <emph>CB</emph> is equal to <emph>GK</emph>, and <emph>CG</emph> to <emph>KB</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.34" targOrder="U">I. 34</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>GK</emph> is also equal to <emph>KB</emph>; <emph>CGKB</emph> is equilateral.</hi></p>
      <p>I say next that it is also right-angled.</p>
      <p>For, since <emph>CG</emph> is parallel to <emph>BK</emph>, <hi rend="center">the angles <emph>KBC</emph>, <emph>GCB</emph> are equal to two right angles. [<ref target="elem.1.29" targOrder="U">I. 29</ref>]</hi></p>
      <p>But the angle <emph>KBC</emph> is right; <hi rend="center">therefore the angle <emph>BCG</emph> is also right, so that the opposite angles <emph>CGK</emph>, <emph>GKB</emph> are also right. [<ref target="elem.1.34" targOrder="U">I. 34</ref>]</hi></p>
      <p>Therefore <emph>CGKB</emph> is right-angled; and it was also proved equilateral; <hi rend="center">therefore it is a square; <emph>CB</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="center"><emph>HF</emph> is also a square; and it is described on <emph>HG</emph>, that is <emph>AC</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.34" targOrder="U">I. 34</ref>]</hi></p>
      <p>Therefore the squares <emph>HF</emph>, <emph>KC</emph> are the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <emph>AG</emph> is equal to <emph>GE</emph>, and <emph>AG</emph> is the rectangle <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph>, for <emph>GC</emph> is equal to <emph>CB</emph>, <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>GE</emph> is also equal to the rectangle <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>Therefore <emph>AG</emph>, <emph>GE</emph> are equal to twice the rectangle <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph>. </p>
      <p>But the squares <emph>HF</emph>, <emph>CK</emph> are also the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph>; therefore the four areas <emph>HF</emph>, <emph>CK</emph>, <emph>AG</emph>, <emph>GE</emph> are equal to the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph> and twice the rectangle contained by <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph>.</p>
      <p>But <emph>HF</emph>, <emph>CK</emph>, <emph>AG</emph>, <emph>GE</emph> are the whole <emph>ADEB</emph>, <emph>AB</emph>.</p>
      <p>Therefore the square on <emph>AB</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph> and twice the rectangle contained by <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph>.</p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.
<note n="2" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
        <p><hi rend="bold">twice the rectangle contained by the segments.</hi> By a curious idiom this is in Greek <quote>the rectangle <emph>twice contained</emph> by the segments.</quote>
 Similarly <quote>twice the rectangle contained by <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph></quote>
 is expressed as <quote>the rectangle <emph>twice contained</emph> by <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph></quote>
 (<foreign lang="greek">τὸ δὶς ὑπὸ τῶν ΑΓ, ΓΒ περιεχόμενον ὀρθογ&lt;*&gt;ώνιον</foreign>).</p>
       </note>
       <note n="35, 38" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
        <p><hi rend="bold">described.</hi> 39, 45. <hi rend="bold">the squares</hi> (before <quote>on</quote>
). These words are not in the Greek, which simply says that the squares <quote>are on</quote>
 (<foreign lang="greek">εἰσἱν ἀπό</foreign>) their respective sides.</p>
       </note>
       <note n="46" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
        <p><hi rend="bold">areas.</hi> It is necessary to supply some substantive (the Greek leaves it to be understood); and I prefer <quote>areas</quote>
 to <quote>figures.</quote>
</p>
       </note></p>
     </div3>
     
