<div3 id="elem.9.14" n="14" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 14.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If a number be the least that is measured by prime numbers, it will not be measured by any other prime number except those originally measuring it.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the number <hi rend="ital">A</hi> be the least that is measured by the prime numbers <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; <hi rend="ital">A</hi> will not be measured by any other prime number except <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, if possible, let it be measured by the prime number <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">E</hi> not be the same with any one of the numbers <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, let it measure it according to <hi rend="ital">F</hi>; <hi rend="center">therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">F</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">A</hi>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is measured by the prime numbers <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, if two numbers by multiplying one another make some number, and any prime number measure the product, it will also measure one of the original numbers; [<ref target="elem.7.30" targOrder="U">VII. 30</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> will measure one of the numbers <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now they will not measure <hi rend="ital">E</hi>; for <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is prime and not the same with any one of the numbers <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore they will measure <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, which is less than <hi rend="ital">A</hi>: which is impossible, for <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is by hypothesis the least number measured by <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore no prime number will measure <hi rend="ital">A</hi> except <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
