<div3 id="elem.10.70" n="70" type="propositions 48&#x2014;84">
      <head>PROPOSITION 70.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">A straight line commensurable with the side of the sum of two medial areas is the side of the sum of two medial areas</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be the side of the sum of two medial areas, and <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> commensurable with <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>; it is to be proved that <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is also the side of the sum of two medial areas. </p>
      <p>For, since <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is the side of the sum of two medial areas, <hi rend="ital">E</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> are straight lines incommensurable in square which make the sum of the squares on them medial, the rectangle contained by them medial, and furthermore the sum of the squares on <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> incommensurable with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EB</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.41" targOrder="U">X. 41</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let the same construction be made as before. </p>
      <p>We can then prove similarly that <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> are also incommensurable in square, the sum of the squares on <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is commensurable with the sum of the squares on <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>, and the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>; so that the sum of the squares on <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> is also medial, the rectangle <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> is medial, and moreover the sum of the squares on <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> is incommensurable with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is the side of the sum of two medial areas. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
