<div3 id="elem.3.16" n="16" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 16.</head>
      <p><emph>The straight line drawn at right angles to the diameter of a circle from its extremity will fall outside the circle</emph>, <emph>and into the space between the straight line and the circumference another straight line cannot be interposed; further the angle of the semicircle is greater</emph>, <emph>and the remaining angle less</emph>, <emph>than any acute rectilineal angle</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>ABC</emph> be a circle about <emph>D</emph> as centre and <emph>AB</emph> as diameter; <emph>A</emph> at right angles to <emph>AB</emph> from its extremity will fall outside the circle. </p>
      <p>For suppose it does not, but, if possible, let it fall within as <emph>CA</emph>, and let <emph>DC</emph> be joined. </p>
      <p>Since <emph>DA</emph> is equal to <emph>DC</emph>, <hi rend="center">the angle <emph>DAC</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>ACD</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.5" targOrder="U">I. 5</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But the angle <emph>DAC</emph> is right; <hi rend="center">therefore the angle <emph>ACD</emph> is also right:</hi> thus, in the triangle <emph>ACD</emph>, the two angles <emph>DAC</emph>, <emph>ACD</emph> are equal to two right angles: which is impossible. [<ref target="elem.1.17" targOrder="U">I. 17</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore the straight line drawn from the point <emph>A</emph> at right angles to <emph>BA</emph> will not fall within the circle. </p>
      <p>Similarly we can prove that neither will it fall on the circumference; <hi rend="center">therefore it will fall outside.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let it fall as <emph>AE</emph>; I say next that into the space between the straight line <emph>AE</emph> and the circumference <emph>CHA</emph> another straight line cannot be interposed. </p>
      <p>For, if possible, let another straight line be so interposed, as <emph>FA</emph>, and let <emph>DG</emph> be drawn from the point <emph>D</emph> perpendicular to <emph>FA</emph>. </p>
      <p>Then, since the angle <emph>AGD</emph> is right, <hi rend="center">and the angle <emph>DAG</emph> is less than a right angle, <emph>AD</emph> is greater than <emph>DG</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.19" targOrder="U">I. 19</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But <emph>DA</emph> is equal to <emph>DH</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>DH</emph> is greater than <emph>DG</emph>, the less than the greater: which is impossible.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore another straight line cannot be interposed into the space between the straight line and the circumference. </p>
      <p>I say further that the angle of the semicircle contained by the straight line <emph>BA</emph> and the circumference <emph>CHA</emph> is greater than any acute rectilineal angle, and the remaining angle contained by the circumference <emph>CHA</emph> and the straight line <emph>AE</emph> is less than any acute rectilineal angle. </p>
      <p>For, if there is any rectilineal angle greater than the angle contained by the straight line <emph>BA</emph> and the circumference <emph>CHA</emph>, and any rectilineal angle less than the angle contained by the circumference <emph>CHA</emph> and the straight line <emph>AE</emph>, then into the space between the circumference and the straight line <emph>AE</emph> a straight line will be interposed such as will make an angle contained by straight lines which is greater than the angle contained by the straight line <emph>BA</emph> and the circumference <emph>CHA</emph>, and another angle contained by straight lines which is less than the angle contained by the circumference <emph>CHA</emph> and the straight line <emph>AE</emph>. </p>
      <p>But such a straight line cannot be interposed; </p>
      <p>therefore there will not be any acute angle contained by straight lines which is greater than the angle contained by the straight line <emph>BA</emph> and the circumference <emph>CHA</emph>, nor yet any acute angle contained by straight lines which is less than the angle contained by the circumference <emph>CHA</emph> and the straight line <emph>AE</emph>.— </p>
      <div4 id="elem.3.16.p.1" type="porism">
       <head>PORISM.</head>
       <p>From this it is manifest that the straight line drawn at right angles to the diameter of a circle from its extremity touches the circle. Q. E. D.</p>
      </div4>
      <note n="4" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p><hi rend="bold">cannot be interposed</hi>, literally <quote>will not fall in between</quote>
 (<foreign lang="greek">οὐ παρεμπεσεῖται</foreign>).</p>
      </note>
     </div3>
     
