<div3 id="elem.10.72" n="72" type="propositions 48&#x2014;84">
      <head>PROPOSITION 72.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If two medial areas incommensurable with one another be added together, the remaining two irrational straight lines arise, namely either a second bimedial or a side of the sum of two medial areas</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let two medial areas <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> incommensurable with one another be added together; I say that the <quote>side</quote>
 of the area <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is either a second bimedial or a side of the sum of two medial areas. </p>
      <p>For <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is either greater or less than <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>First, if it so chance, let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be greater than <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> be set out, and to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> let there be applied the rectangle <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> and producing <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> as breadth, and the rectangle <hi rend="ital">HI</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> and producing <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> as breadth. </p>
      <p>Now, since each of the areas <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is medial, therefore each of the areas <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HI</hi> is also medial. </p>
      <p>And they are applied to the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">FE</hi>, producing <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> as breadth; therefore each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> is rational and incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.22" targOrder="U">X. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> to <hi rend="ital">HI</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is also incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">HI</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">HI</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> to <hi rend="ital">HK</hi>; [<ref target="elem.6.1" targOrder="U">VI. 1</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">HK</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.11" targOrder="U">X. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> is binomial. [<ref target="elem.10.36" targOrder="U">X. 36</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> either by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> or by the square on a straight line incommensurable with it. </p>
      <p>First, let the square on it be greater by the square on a straight line commensurable in length with itself. </p>
      <p>Now neither of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> set out; therefore <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> is a third binomial. [<ref target="elem.10.def.2.3" targOrder="U">X. Deff. II. 3</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is rational; and, if an area be contained by a rational straight line and the third binomial, the <quote>side</quote>
 of the area is a second bimedial; [<ref target="elem.10.56" targOrder="U">X. 56</ref>] therefore the <quote>side</quote>
 of <hi rend="ital">EI</hi>, that is, of <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, is a second bimedial. </p>
      <p>Next, let the square on <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> be greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> is a sixth binomial. [<ref target="elem.10.def.2.6" targOrder="U">X. Deff. II. 6</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, if an area be contained by a rational straight line and <quote>side</quote>
 of the area is the side of the sum of two medial areas; [<ref target="elem.10.59" targOrder="U">X. 59</ref>] so that the <quote>side</quote>
 of the area <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is also the side of the sum of two medial areas. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
