<div3 id="elem.10.79" n="79" type="propositions 48&#x2014;84">
      <head>PROPOSITION 79</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">To an apotome only one rational straight line can be annexed which is commensurable with the whole in square only</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be an apotome, and <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> an annex to it; therefore <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only. [<ref target="elem.10.73" targOrder="U">X. 73</ref>] </p>
      <p>I say that no other rational straight line can be annexed to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> which is commensurable with the whole in square only. </p>
      <p>For, if possible, let <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> be so annexed; therefore <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> are also rational straight lines commensurable in square only. [<ref target="elem.10.73" targOrder="U">X. 73</ref>] </p>
      <p>Now, since the excess of the squares on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> over twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> is also the excess of the squares on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> over twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, for both exceed by the same, the square on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, [<ref target="elem.2.7" targOrder="U">II. 7</ref>] <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> over the squares on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> is the excess of twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> over twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the squares on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> exceed the squares on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> by a rational area, for both are rational; therefore twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> also exceeds twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> by a rational area: which is impossible, for both are medial [<ref target="elem.10.21" targOrder="U">X. 21</ref>], and a medial area does not exceed a medial by a rational area. [<ref target="elem.10.26" targOrder="U">X. 26</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore no other rational straight line can be annexed to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> which is commensurable with the whole in square only. </p>
      <p>Therefore only one rational straight line can be annexed to an apotome which is commensurable with the whole in square only. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
