<div3 id="elem.10.61" n="61" type="propositions 48&#x2014;84">
      <head>PROPOSITION 61.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">The square on the first bimedial straight line applied to a rational straight line produces as breadth the second binomial</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be a first bimedial straight line divided into its medials at <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, of which medials <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is the greater; let a rational straight line <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> be set out, and let there be applied to <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, producing <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> as its breadth; I say that <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> is a second binominal straight line. </p>
      <p>For let the same construction as before be made. </p>
      <p>Then, since <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is a first bimedial divided at <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> are medial straight lines commensurable in square only, and containing a rational rectangle, [<ref target="elem.10.37" targOrder="U">X. 37</ref>] so that the squares on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> are also medial. [<ref target="elem.10.21" targOrder="U">X. 21</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">DL</hi> is medial. [<ref target="elem.10.15 elem.10.23.p.1" targOrder="U">X. 15 and 23, Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>And it has been applied to the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">MD</hi> is rational and incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.22" targOrder="U">X. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>Again, since twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> is rational, <hi rend="ital">MF</hi> is also rational. </p>
      <p>And it is applied to the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">ML</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">MG</hi> is also rational and commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">ML</hi>, that is, <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>; [<ref target="elem.10.20" targOrder="U">X. 20</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">DM</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">MG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.13" targOrder="U">X. 13</ref>] </p>
      <p>And they are rational; therefore <hi rend="ital">DM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MG</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> is binomial. [<ref target="elem.10.36" targOrder="U">X. 36</ref>] </p>
      <p>It is next to be proved that it is also a second binomial straight line. </p>
      <p>For, since the squares on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> are greater than twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">DL</hi> is also greater than <hi rend="ital">MF</hi>, so that <hi rend="ital">DM</hi> is also greater than <hi rend="ital">MG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.1" targOrder="U">VI. 1</ref>] </p>
      <p>And, since the square on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DH</hi> is also commensurable with <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>, so that <hi rend="ital">DK</hi> is also commensurable with <hi rend="ital">KM</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.1" targOrder="U">VI. 1</ref>, <ref target="elem.10.11" targOrder="U">X. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>And the rectangle <hi rend="ital">DK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KM</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">MN</hi>; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">DM</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">MG</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">DM</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.17" targOrder="U">X. 17</ref>] </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">MG</hi> is commensurable is length with <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> is a second binomial straight line. [<ref target="elem.10.def.2.2" targOrder="U">X. Deff. II. 2</ref>]</p>
     </div3>
     
