<div3 id="elem.11.10" n="10" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 10.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If two straight lines meeting one another be parallel to two straight lines meeting one another not in the same plane</hi>, <hi rend="ital">they will contain equal angles.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the two straight lines <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> meeting one another be parallel to the two straight lines <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> meeting one another, not in the same plane; I say that the angle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">ED</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> be cut off equal to one another, and let <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> be joined. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is equal and parallel to <hi rend="ital">ED</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is also equal and parallel to <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.33" targOrder="U">I. 33</ref>] </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> is also equal and parallel to <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> is equal and parallel to <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>. </p>
      <p>But straight lines which are parallel to the same straight line and are not in the same plane with it are parallel to one another; [<ref target="elem.11.9" targOrder="U">XI. 9</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is parallel and equal to <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>. </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> join them; therefore <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is also equal and parallel to <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.33" targOrder="U">I. 33</ref>] </p>
      <p>Now, since the two sides <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are equal to the two sides <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, and the base <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is equal to the base <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.8" targOrder="U">I. 8</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore etc.</p>
     </div3>
     
