<div3 id="elem.10.88" n="88" type="propositions 85&#x2014;115">
      <head>PROPOSITION 88.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">To find the fourth apotome</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let a rational straight line <hi rend="ital">A</hi> be set out, and <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> commensurable in length with it; therefore <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is also rational. </p>
      <p>Let two numbers <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FE</hi> be set out such that the whole <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> has not to either of the numbers <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number. </p>
      <p>Let it be contrived that, as <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GC</hi>; [<ref target="elem.10.6.p.1" targOrder="U">X. 6, Por.</ref>] therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">GC</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.6" targOrder="U">X. 6</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is rational; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> is also rational; therefore <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> is rational. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> has not to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number, therefore neither has the square on <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">GC</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] </p>
      <p>And both are rational; therefore <hi rend="ital">BG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is an apotome. [<ref target="elem.10.73" targOrder="U">X. 73</ref>] </p>
      <p>Now let the square on <hi rend="ital">H</hi> be that by which the square on <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">GC</hi>. </p>
      <p>Since then, as <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GC</hi>, therefore also, <foreign lang="la">convertendo</foreign>, as <hi rend="ital">ED</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">GB</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">H</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.19.p.1" targOrder="U">v. 19, Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">ED</hi> has not to <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore neither has the square on <hi rend="ital">GB</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">H</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] </p>
      <p>And the square on <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> by the square on <hi rend="ital">H</hi>; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">BG</hi>. </p>
      <p>And the whole <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">A</hi> set out. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is a fourth apotome. [<ref target="elem.10.def.3.4" targOrder="U">X. Deff. III. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore the fourth apotome has been found. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
