<div3 id="elem.11.18" n="18" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 18.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If a straight line be at right angles to any plane</hi>, <hi rend="ital">all the planes through it will also be at right angles to the same plane.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let any straight line <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be at right angles to the plane of reference; I say that all the planes through <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> are also at right angles to the plane of reference. </p>
      <p>For let the plane <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> be drawn through <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, let <hi rend="ital">CE</hi> be the common section of the plane <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> and the plane of reference, let a point <hi rend="ital">F</hi> be taken at random on <hi rend="ital">CE</hi>, and from <hi rend="ital">F</hi> let <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> be drawn in the plane <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> at right angles to <hi rend="ital">CE</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.11" targOrder="U">I. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is at right angles to the plane of reference, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is also at right angles to all the straight lines which meet it and are in the plane of reference; [<ref target="elem.11.def.3" targOrder="U">XI. Def. 3</ref>] so that it is also at right angles to <hi rend="ital">CE</hi>; therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">ABF</hi> is right. </p>
      <p>But the angle <hi rend="ital">GFB</hi> is also right; therefore <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is parallel to <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.28" targOrder="U">I. 28</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is at right angles to the plane of reference; therefore <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is also at right angles to the plane of reference. [<ref target="elem.11.8" targOrder="U">XI. 8</ref>] </p>
      <p>Now a plane is at right angles to a plane, when the straight lines drawn, in one of the planes, at right angles to the common section of the planes are at right angles to the remaining plane. [<ref target="elem.11.def.4" targOrder="U">XI. Def. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, drawn in one of the planes <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> at right angles to <hi rend="ital">CE</hi>, the common section of the planes, was proved to be at right angles to the plane of reference; therefore the plane <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is at right angles to the plane of reference. </p>
      <p>Similarly also it can be proved that all the planes through <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> are at right angles to the plane of reference. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
