<div3 id="elem.10.109" n="109" type="propositions 85&#x2014;115">
      <head>PROPOSITION 109.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If from a medial area a rational area be subtracted, there arise two other irrational straight lines, either a first apotome of a medial straight line or a straight line which produces with a rational area a medial whole</hi>. </p>
      <p>For from the medial area <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> let the rational area <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> be subtracted. </p>
      <p>I say that the <quote>side</quote>
 of the remainder <hi rend="ital">EC</hi> becomes one of two irrational straight lines, either a first apotome of a medial straight line or a straight line which produces with a rational area a medial whole. </p>
      <p>For let a rational straight line <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> be set out, and let the areas be similarly applied. </p>
      <p>It follows then that <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> is rational and incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, while <hi rend="ital">KF</hi> is rational and commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; [<ref target="elem.10.13" targOrder="U">X. 13</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> is an apotome, and <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> the annex to it. [<ref target="elem.10.73" targOrder="U">X. 73</ref>] </p>
      <p>Now the square on <hi rend="ital">HF</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> either by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">HF</hi> or by the square on a straight line incommensurable with it. </p>
      <p>If then the square on <hi rend="ital">HF</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">HF</hi>, while the annex <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> set out, <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> is a second apotome. [<ref target="elem.10.def.3.2" targOrder="U">X. Deff. III. 2</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is rational; so that the <quote>side</quote>
 of <hi rend="ital">LH</hi>, that is, of <hi rend="ital">EC</hi>, is a first apotome of a medial straight line. [<ref target="elem.10.92" targOrder="U">X. 92</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, if the square on <hi rend="ital">HF</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">HF</hi>, while the annex <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> set out, <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> is a fifth apotome; [<ref target="elem.10.def.3.5" targOrder="U">X. Deff. III. 5</ref>] so that the <quote>side</quote>
 of <hi rend="ital">EC</hi> is a straight line which produces with a rational area a medial whole. [<ref target="elem.10.95" targOrder="U">X. 95</ref>]</p>
     </div3>
     
