<div3 id="elem.9.18" n="18" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 18.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">Given two numbers, to investigate whether it is possible to find a third proportional to them.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> be the given two numbers, and let it be required to investigate whether it is possible to find a third proportional to them. </p>
      <p>Now <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> are either prime to one another or not. </p>
      <p>And, if they are prime to one another, it has been proved that it is impossible to find a third proportional to them. [<ref target="elem.9.16" targOrder="U">IX. 16</ref>] </p>
      <p>Next, let <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> not be prime to one another, and let <hi rend="ital">B</hi> by multiplying itself make <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>Then <hi rend="ital">A</hi> either measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi> or does not measure it. </p>
      <p>First, let it measure it according to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">D</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, further, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> has also by multiplying itself made <hi rend="ital">C</hi>; therefore the product of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">B</hi> to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; [<ref target="elem.7.19" targOrder="U">VII. 19</ref>] therefore a third proportional number <hi rend="ital">D</hi> has been found to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>Next, let <hi rend="ital">A</hi> not measure <hi rend="ital">C</hi>; I say that it is impossible to find a third proportional number to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, if possible, let <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, such third proportional, have been found. </p>
      <p>Therefore the product of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is <hi rend="ital">C</hi>; therefore the product of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>Hence <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">D</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">C</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi> according to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, by hypothesis, it also does not measure it: which is absurd. </p>
      <p>Therefore it is not possible to find a third proportional number to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> when <hi rend="ital">A</hi> does not measure <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
