<div3 id="elem.7.7" n="7" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 7.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If a number be that part of a number, which a number subtracted is of a number subtracted, the remainder will also be the same part of the remainder that the whole is of the whole.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the number <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be that part of the number <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> which <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> subtracted is of <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> subtracted; I say that the remainder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is also the same part of the remainder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> that the whole <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is of the whole <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, the same part also let <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> be of <hi rend="ital">CG</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now since, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, the same part also is <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> of <hi rend="ital">CG</hi>, therefore, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, the same part also is <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> of <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.5" targOrder="U">VII. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, the same part also, by hypothesis, is <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> of <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>; therefore, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>, the same part is it of <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> also; therefore <hi rend="ital">GF</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> be subtracted from each; therefore the remainder <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> is equal to the remainder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now since, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, the same part also is <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> of <hi rend="ital">GC</hi>, while <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>, therefore, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, the same part also is <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> of <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, the same part also is <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> of <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>; <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is the same part of the remainder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> that the whole <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is of the whole <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
