<div3 id="elem.10.111" n="111" type="propositions 85&#x2014;115">
      <head>PROPOSITION 111.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">The apotome is not the same with the binomial straight line</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be an apotome; I say that <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is not the same with the binomial straight line. </p>
      <p>For, if possible, let it be so; let a rational straight line <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> be set out, and to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> let there be applied the rectangle <hi rend="ital">CE</hi> equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> and producing <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> as breadth. </p>
      <p>Then, since <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is an apotome, <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is a first apotome. [<ref target="elem.10.97" targOrder="U">X. 97</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> be the annex to it; therefore <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FE</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only, the square on <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">FE</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> set out. [<ref target="elem.10.def.3.1" targOrder="U">X. Deff. III. 1</ref>] </p>
      <p>Again, since <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is binomial, therefore <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is a first binomial straight line. [<ref target="elem.10.60" targOrder="U">X. 60</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let it be divided into its terms at <hi rend="ital">G</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> be the greater term; therefore <hi rend="ital">DG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GE</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only, <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">GE</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">DG</hi>, and the greater term <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> set out. [<ref target="elem.10.def.2.1" targOrder="U">X. Deff. II. 1</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> is also commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">DG</hi>; [<ref target="elem.10.12" targOrder="U">X. 12</ref>] therefore the remainder <hi rend="ital">GF</hi> is also commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.15" targOrder="U">X. 15</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is also incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.13" targOrder="U">X. 13</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FE</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is an apotome. [<ref target="elem.10.73" targOrder="U">X. 73</ref>] </p>
      <p>But it is also rational: which is impossible. </p>
      <p>Therefore the apotome is not the same with the binomial straight line. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
