<div3 id="elem.10.48" n="48" type="propositions 48&#x2014;84">
      <head>PROPOSITION 48.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">To find the first binomial straight line</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let two numbers <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> be set out such that the sum of them <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number, but has not to <hi rend="ital">CA</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; [<ref target="elem.10.28.l.1" targOrder="U">Lemma I after X. 28</ref>] <hi rend="ital">D</hi> be set out, and let <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> be commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is also rational. </p>
      <p>Let it be contrived that, as the number <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.6.p.1" targOrder="U">X. 6, Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> the ratio which a number has to a number; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> also has to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> the ratio which a number has to a number, so that the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.6" targOrder="U">X. 6</ref>] </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is rational; therefore <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is also rational. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> has not to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number. <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is binomial. [<ref target="elem.10.36" targOrder="U">X. 36</ref>] </p>
      <p>I say that it is also a first binomial straight line. </p>
      <p>For since, as the number <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, while <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is greater than <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is also greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let then the squares on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">H</hi> be equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now since, as <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, therefore, <hi rend="ital">convertendo</hi>, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">H</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.19.p.1" targOrder="U">V. 19, Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> also has to the square on <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">H</hi>; [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>. </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> are rational, and <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is a first binomial straight line. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
