<div3 id="elem.1.14" n="14" type="proposition">
      <head>Proposition 14.</head>
      <div4 type="Enunc">
       <p>If with any straight line, and at a point on it, two straight lines not lying on the same side make the adjacent angles equal to two right angles, the two straight lines will be in a straight line with one another. </p>
      </div4>
      <div4 type="Proof">
       <p>For with any straight line <emph>AB</emph>, and at the point <emph>B</emph> on it, let the two straight lines <emph>BC</emph>, <emph>BD</emph> not lying on the same side make the adjacent angles <emph>ABC</emph>, <emph>ABD</emph> equal to two right angles;</p>
       <p>I say that <emph>BD</emph> is in a straight line with <emph>CB</emph>. </p>
       <p>For, if <emph>BD</emph> is not in a straight line with <emph>BC</emph>, let <emph>BE</emph> be in a straight line with <emph>CB</emph>.</p>
       <p>Then, since the straight line <emph>AB</emph> stands on the straight line <emph>CBE</emph>, <hi rend="center">the angles <emph>ABC</emph>, <emph>ABE</emph> are equal to two right angles. [<ref target="elem.1.13" targOrder="U">I. 13</ref>]</hi> But the angles <emph>ABC</emph>, <emph>ABD</emph> are also equal to two right angles; <hi rend="center">therefore the angles <emph>CBA</emph>, <emph>ABE</emph> are equal to the angles <emph>CBA</emph>, <emph>ABD</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.post.4" targOrder="U">Post. 4</ref> and <ref target="elem.1.c.n.1" targOrder="U">C.N. 1</ref>]</hi></p>
       <p>Let the angle <emph>CBA</emph> be subtracted from each; <emph>ABE</emph> is equal to the remaining angle <emph>ABD</emph>, [<ref target="elem.1.c.n.3" targOrder="U">C.N. 3</ref>] <hi rend="center">the less to the greater: which is impossible. Therefore <emph>BE</emph> is not in a straight line with <emph>CB</emph>.</hi></p>
       <p>Similarly we can prove that neither is any other straight <emph>BD</emph>. <hi rend="center">Therefore <emph>CB</emph> is in a straight line with <emph>BD</emph>.</hi></p>
       <p>Therefore etc.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 type="QED">
       <p>Q. E. D.</p>
      </div4>
      <note n="1. If with any straight line...." type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p>There is no greater difficulty in translating the works of the Greek geometers than that of accurately giving the force of prepositions. <foreign lang="greek">πρός</foreign>, for instance, is used in all sorts of expressions with various shades of meaning. The present enunciation begins <foreign lang="greek">ἐὰν πρός τινι εὐθείᾳ καὶ τῷ πρὸς αὐτῆ σημείῳ</foreign>, and it is really necessary in this one sentence to translate <foreign lang="greek">πρός</foreign> by three different words, <emph>with</emph>, <emph>at</emph>, and <emph>on</emph>. The first <foreign lang="greek">πρός</foreign> must be translated by <emph>with</emph> because two straight lines <quote>make</quote>
 an angle <emph>with</emph> one another. On the other hand, where the similar expression <foreign lang="greek">πρὸς τῇ δοθείση εὐθείᾳ</foreign> occurs in <ref target="elem.1.23" targOrder="U">I. 23</ref>, but it is a question of <quote>constructing</quote>
 an angle (<foreign lang="greek">συστἡσασθαι</foreign>), we have to say <quote>to construct <emph>on</emph> a given straight line.</quote>
 <title>Against</title> would perhaps be the English word coming nearest to expressing all these meanings of <foreign lang="greek">πρός</foreign>, but it would be intolerable as a translation.</p>
      </note>
      <note n="17" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p>Todhunter points out that for the inference in this line <ref target="elem.1.post.4" targOrder="U">Post. 4</ref>, that all right angles are equal, is necessary as well as the Common Notion that things which are equal to the same thing (or rather, here, to <emph>equal things</emph>) are equal. A similar remark applies to steps in the proofs of <ref target="elem.1.15" targOrder="U">I. 15</ref> and <ref target="elem.1.28" targOrder="U">I. 28</ref>.</p>
      </note>
      <note n="24. we can prove." type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p>The Greek expresses this by the future of the verb, <foreign lang="greek">δείξομεν</foreign>, <quote>we shall prove,</quote>
 which however would perhaps be misleading in English.</p>
      </note>
     </div3>
     
