<div3 id="elem.11.22" n="22" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 22.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If there be three plane angles of which two</hi>, <hi rend="ital">taken together in any manner</hi>, <hi rend="ital">are greater than the remaining one</hi>, <hi rend="ital">and they are contained by equal straight lines</hi>, <hi rend="ital">it is possible to construct a triangle out of the straight lines joining the extremities of the equal straight lines.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let there be three plane angles <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi>, of <hi rend="center">the angles <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> greater than the angle <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi>, the angles <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> greater than the angle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>,</hi> and, further, the angles <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> greater than the angle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>; let the straight lines <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> be equal, and let <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GK</hi> be joined; I say that it is possible to construct a triangle out of straight lines equal to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GK</hi>, that is, that any two of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GK</hi> are greater than the remaining one. </p>
      <p>Now, if the angles <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> are equal to one another, it is manifest that, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GK</hi> being equal also, it is possible to construct a triangle out of straight lines equal to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GK</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, if not, let them be unequal, and on the straight line <hi rend="ital">HK</hi>, and at the point <hi rend="ital">H</hi> on it, let the angle <hi rend="ital">KHL</hi> be constructed equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>; let <hi rend="ital">HL</hi> be made equal to one of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GL</hi> be joined. </p>
      <p>Now, since the two sides <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are equal to the two sides <hi rend="ital">KH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HL</hi>, and the angle at <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KHL</hi>, therefore the base <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is equal to the base <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.4" targOrder="U">I. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>And, since the angles <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GHK</hi> are greater than the angle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KHL</hi>, therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">GHL</hi> is greater than the angle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, since the two sides <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HL</hi> are equal to the two sides <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, and the angle <hi rend="ital">GHL</hi> is greater than the angle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, therefore the base <hi rend="ital">GL</hi> is greater than the base <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.24" targOrder="U">I. 24</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">GK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> are greater than <hi rend="ital">GL</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">GK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> are much greater than <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GK</hi> are greater than the remaining straight line <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>. </p>
      <p>Similarly we can prove that <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> are greater than <hi rend="ital">GK</hi>, and further <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GK</hi> are greater than <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore it is possible to construct a triangle out of straight lines equal to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GK</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
