<div3 id="elem.10.16" n="16" type="propositions i&#x2014;47">
      <head>PROPOSITION 16.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If two incommensurable magnitudes be added together, the whole will also be incommensurable with each of them; and, if the whole be incommensurable with one of them, the original magnitudes will also be incommensurable</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let the two incommensurable magnitudes <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> be added together; I say that the whole <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is also incommensurable with each of the magnitudes <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, if <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> are not incommensurable, some magnitude will measure them. </p>
      <p>Let it measure them, if possible, and let it be <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Since then <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, therefore it will also measure the remainder <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it measures <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> also; therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are commensurable; but they were also, by hypothesis, incommensurable: which is impossible. </p>
      <p>Therefore no magnitude will measure <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> are incommensurable. [<ref target="elem.10.def.1" targOrder="U">X. Def. 1</ref>] </p>
      <p>Similarly we can prove that <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> are also incommensurable. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is incommensurable with each of the magnitudes <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>Next, let <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> be incommensurable with one of the magnitudes <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>First, let it be incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>; I say that <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are also incommensurable. </p>
      <p>For, if they are commensurable, some magnitude will measure them. </p>
      <p>Let it measure them, and let it be <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Since then <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. therefore it will also measure the whole <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it measures <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> also; therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> are commensurable; but they were also, by hypothesis, incommensurable: which is impossible. </p>
      <p>Therefore no magnitude will measure <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are incommensurable. [<ref target="elem.10.def.1" targOrder="U">X. Def. 1</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore etc.</p>
      <div4 id="elem.10.16.l.1" type="lemma">
       <head>LEMMA.</head>
       <p>
        <hi rend="ital">If to any straight line there be applied a parallelogram deficient by a square figure, the applied parallelogram is equal to the rectangle contained by the segments of the straight line resulting from the application.</hi>
       </p>
       <p>For let there be applied to the straight line <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> deficient by the square figure <hi rend="ital">DB</hi>; I say that <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is equal to the rectangle contained by <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. </p>
       <p>This is indeed at once manifest; for, since <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> is a square, <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>; and <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, that is, the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. </p>
       <p>Therefore etc.</p>
      </div4>
     </div3>
     
