<div3 id="elem.3.15" n="15" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 15.</head>
      <p><emph>Of straight lines in a circle the diameter is greatest</emph>, <emph>and of the rest the nearer to the centre is always greater than the more remote</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>ABCD</emph> be a circle, let <emph>AD</emph> be its diameter and <emph>E</emph> the centre; and let <emph>BC</emph> be nearer to the diameter <emph>AD</emph>, and <emph>FG</emph> more remote; I say that <emph>AD</emph> is greatest and <emph>BC</emph> greater than <emph>FG</emph>. </p>
      <p>For from the centre <emph>E</emph> let <emph>EH</emph>, <emph>EK</emph>
       <emph>BC</emph>, <emph>FG</emph>. </p>
      <p>Then, since <emph>BC</emph> is nearer to the centre and <emph>FG</emph> more remote, <emph>EK</emph> is greater than <emph>EH</emph>. [<ref target="elem.3.def.5" targOrder="U">III. Def. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let <emph>EL</emph> be made equal to <emph>EH</emph>, through <emph>L</emph> let <emph>LM</emph> be drawn at right angles to <emph>EK</emph> and carried through to <emph>N</emph>, and let <emph>ME</emph>, <emph>EN</emph>, <emph>FE</emph>, <emph>EG</emph> be joined. </p>
      <p>Then, since <emph>EH</emph> is equal to <emph>EL</emph>, <hi rend="center"><emph>BC</emph> is also equal to <emph>MN</emph>. [<ref target="elem.3.14" targOrder="U">III. 14</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Again, since <emph>AE</emph> is equal to <emph>EM</emph>, and <emph>ED</emph> to <emph>EN</emph>, <hi rend="center"><emph>AD</emph> is equal to <emph>ME</emph>, <emph>EN</emph>.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>But <emph>ME</emph>, <emph>EN</emph> are greater than <emph>MN</emph>, [<ref target="elem.1.20" targOrder="U">I. 20</ref>] and <emph>MN</emph> is equal to <emph>BC</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>AD</emph> is greater than <emph>BC</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And, since the two sides <emph>ME</emph>, <emph>EN</emph> are equal to the two sides <emph>FE</emph>, <emph>EG</emph>, and the angle <emph>MEN</emph> greater than the angle <emph>FEG</emph>, therefore the base <emph>MN</emph> is greater than the base <emph>FG</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.24" targOrder="U">I. 24</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <emph>MN</emph> was proved equal to <emph>BC</emph>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the diameter <emph>AD</emph> is greatest and <emph>BC</emph> greater than <emph>FG</emph>. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.
<note n="1" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
        <p><hi rend="bold">Of straight lines</hi>. The Greek leaves these words to be understood.</p>
       </note>
       <note n="5" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
        <p><hi rend="bold">Nearer to the diameter AD.</hi> As <emph>BC</emph>, <emph>FG</emph> are not in general parallel to <emph>AD</emph>, Euclid should have said <quote>nearer to the centre.</quote>
</p>
       </note></p>
     </div3>
     
