<div3 id="elem.3.14" n="14" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 14.</head>
      <p><emph>In a circle equal straight lines are equally distant from the centre</emph>, <emph>and those which are equally distant from the centre are equal to one another</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>ABDC</emph> be a circle, and let <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>CD</emph> be equal straight lines in it; I say that <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>CD</emph> are equally distant from the centre. </p>
      <p>For let the centre of the circle <emph>ABDC</emph> be taken [<ref target="elem.3.1" targOrder="U">III. 1</ref>], <emph>E</emph>; from <emph>E</emph> let <emph>EF</emph>, <emph>EG</emph> be drawn perpendicular to <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>CD</emph>, and let <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> be joined. </p>
      <p>Then, since a straight line <emph>EF</emph> through the centre cuts a straight line <emph>AB</emph> not through the centre at right angles, it also bisects it. [<ref target="elem.3.3" targOrder="U">III. 3</ref>] <hi rend="center">Therefore <emph>AF</emph> is equal to <emph>FB</emph>; therefore <emph>AB</emph> is double of <emph>AF</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="center"><emph>CD</emph> is also double of <emph>CG</emph>;</hi> and <emph>AB</emph> is equal to <emph>CD</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>AF</emph> is also equal to <emph>CG</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And, since <emph>AE</emph> is equal to <emph>EC</emph>, <hi rend="center">the square on <emph>AE</emph> is also equal to the square on <emph>EC</emph>.</hi> But the squares on <emph>AF</emph>, <emph>EF</emph> are equal to the square on <emph>AE</emph>, for the angle at <emph>F</emph> is right; and the squares on <emph>EG</emph>, <emph>GC</emph> are equal to the square on <emph>EC</emph>, for the angle at <emph>G</emph> is right; [<ref target="elem.1.47" targOrder="U">I. 47</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore the squares on <emph>AF</emph>, <emph>FE</emph> are equal to the squares on <emph>CG</emph>, <emph>GE</emph>,</hi> of which the square on <emph>AF</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>CG</emph>, for <emph>AF</emph> is equal to <emph>CG</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the square on <emph>FE</emph> which remains is equal to the square on <emph>EG</emph>, therefore <emph>EF</emph> is equal to <emph>EG</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But in a circle straight lines are said to be equally distant from the centre when the perpendiculars drawn to them from the centre are equal; [<ref target="elem.3.def.4" targOrder="U">III. Def. 4</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>CD</emph> are equally distant from the centre.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Next, let the straight lines <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>CD</emph> be equally distant from the centre; that is, let <emph>EF</emph> be equal to <emph>EG</emph>. </p>
      <p>I say that <emph>AB</emph> is also equal to <emph>CD</emph>. </p>
      <p>For, with the same construction, we can prove, similarly, that <emph>AB</emph> is double of <emph>AF</emph>, and <emph>CD</emph> of <emph>CG</emph>. </p>
      <p>And, since <emph>AE</emph> is equal to <emph>CE</emph>, <hi rend="center">the square on <emph>AE</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>CE</emph>.</hi> But the squares on <emph>EF</emph>, <emph>FA</emph> are equal to the square on <emph>AE</emph>, and the squares on <emph>EG</emph>, <emph>GC</emph> equal to the square on <emph>CE</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.47" targOrder="U">I. 47</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore the squares on <emph>EF</emph>, <emph>FA</emph> are equal to the squares on <emph>EG</emph>, <emph>GC</emph>, of which the square on <emph>EF</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>EG</emph>, for <emph>EF</emph> is equal to <emph>EG</emph>; therefore the square on <emph>AF</emph> which remains is equal to the square on <emph>CG</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>AF</emph> is equal to <emph>CG</emph>.</hi> And <emph>AB</emph> is double of <emph>AF</emph>, and <emph>CD</emph> double of <emph>CG</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>AB</emph> is equal to <emph>CD</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
