<div3 id="elem.7.5" n="5" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 5.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If a number be a part of a number, and another be the same part of another, the sum will also be the same part of the sum that the one is of the one.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the number <hi rend="ital">A</hi> be a part of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, and another, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, the same part of another <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> that <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>; I say that the sum of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is also the same part of the sum of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> that <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>For since, whatever part <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is also the same part of <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, therefore, as many numbers as there are in <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, so many numbers are there also in <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> be divided into the numbers equal to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, namely <hi rend="ital">BG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GC</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> into the numbers equal to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, namely <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HF</hi>; then the multitude of <hi rend="ital">BG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> will be equal to the multitude of <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HF</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">BG</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">BG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> are also equal to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="ital">GC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HF</hi> are also equal to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, as many numbers as there are in <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, so many are there also in <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, whatever multiple <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, the same multiple also is the sum of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> of the sum of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, whatever part <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, the same part also is the sum of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> of the sum of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
