<div3 id="elem.10.32" n="32" type="propositions i&#x2014;47">
      <head>PROPOSITION 32.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">To find two medial straight lines commensurable in square only, containing a medial rectangle, and such that the square on the greater is greater than the square on the less by the square on a straight line commensurable with the greater.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>Let there be set out three rational straight lines <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi> commensurable in square only, and such that the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, [<ref target="elem.10.29" targOrder="U">X. 29</ref>] and let the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> be equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is medial; therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is also medial. [<ref target="elem.10.21" targOrder="U">X. 21</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let the rectangle <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> be equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>Then since, as the rectangle <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>; while the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, and the rectangle <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, therefore, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">D</hi> to <hi rend="ital">E</hi>; therefore also, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">D</hi> to <hi rend="ital">E</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is commensurable with <hi rend="ital">C</hi> in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is also commensurable with <hi rend="ital">E</hi> in square only. [<ref target="elem.10.11" targOrder="U">X. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is medial; therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is also medial. [<ref target="elem.10.23" targOrder="U">X. 23</ref>, addition] </p>
      <p>And, since, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">D</hi> to <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, while the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, therefore also the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> will be greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">E</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">D</hi>.[<ref target="elem.10.14" targOrder="U">X. 14</ref>] </p>
      <p>I say next that the rectangle <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is also medial. </p>
      <p>For, since the rectangle <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, while the rectangle <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is medial, [<ref target="elem.10.21" targOrder="U">X. 21</ref>] therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is also medial. </p>
      <p>Therefore two medial straight lines <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, commensurable in square only, and containing a medial rectangle, have been found such that the square on the greater is greater than the </p>
      <div4 id="elem.10.32.p.1" type="porism">
       <p>Similarly again it can be proved that the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">E</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, when the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.30" targOrder="U">X. 30</ref>]</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 id="elem.10.32.l.1" type="lemma">
       <head>LEMMA.</head>
       <p>Let <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> be a right-angled triangle having the angle <hi rend="ital">A</hi> right, and let the perpendicular <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> be drawn; I say that the rectangle <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, and, further, the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. </p>
       <p>And first that the rectangle <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>. </p>
       <p>For, since in a right-angled triangle <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> has been drawn from the right angle perpendicular to the base, therefore the triangles <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">ADC</hi> are similar both to the whole <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> and to one another. [<ref target="elem.6.8" targOrder="U">VI. 8</ref>] </p>
       <p>And since the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi>, therefore, as <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi>; [<ref target="elem.6.4" targOrder="U">VI. 4</ref>] therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.17" targOrder="U">VI. 17</ref>] </p>
       <p>For the same reason the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is also equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. </p>
       <p>And since, if in a right-angled triangle a perpendicular be drawn from the right angle to the base, the perpendicular so drawn is a mean proportional between the segments of the base, [<ref target="elem.6.8.p.1" targOrder="U">VI. 8, Por.</ref>] therefore, as <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">DA</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> to <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>; therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.17" targOrder="U">VI. 17</ref>] </p>
       <p>I say that the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is also equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. </p>
       <p>For since, as we said, <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is similar to <hi rend="ital">ABD</hi>, therefore, as <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> to <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.4" targOrder="U">VI. 4</ref>] </p>
       <p>Therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.16" targOrder="U">VI. 16</ref>] Q. E. D.</p>
      </div4>
     </div3>
     
