<div3 id="elem.9.12" n="12" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 12.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If as many numbers as we please beginning from an unit be in continued proportion, by however many prime numbers the last is measured, the next to the unit will also be measured by the same.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let there be as many numbers as we please, <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, beginning from an unit, and in continued proportion; I say that, by however many prime numbers <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is measured, <hi rend="ital">A</hi> will also be measured by the same. </p>
      <p>For let <hi rend="ital">D</hi> be measured by any prime number <hi rend="ital">E</hi>; I say that <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. </p>
      <p>For suppose it does not; now <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is prime, and any prime number is prime to any which it does not measure; [<ref target="elem.7.29" targOrder="U">VII. 29</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">A</hi> are prime to one another. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, let it measure it according to <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">F</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Again, since <hi rend="ital">A</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">D</hi> according to the units in <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, [<ref target="elem.9.11 elem.9.11.p.1" targOrder="U">IX. 11 and Por.</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">C</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, further, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> has also by multiplying <hi rend="ital">F</hi> made <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; therefore the product of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is equal to the product of <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">F</hi> to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.19" targOrder="U">VII. 19</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> are prime, primes are also least, [<ref target="elem.7.21" targOrder="U">VII. 21</ref>] and the least measure those which have the same ratio the same number of times, the antecedent the antecedent and the consequent the consequent; [<ref target="elem.7.20" targOrder="U">VII. 20</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let it measure it according to <hi rend="ital">G</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">G</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, further, by the theorem before this, <hi rend="ital">A</hi> has also by multiplying <hi rend="ital">B</hi> made <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. [<ref target="elem.9.11 elem.9.11.p.1" targOrder="U">IX. 11 and Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore the product of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is equal to the product of <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">G</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">G</hi> to <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.19" targOrder="U">VII. 19</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> are prime, primes are also least, [<ref target="elem.7.21" targOrder="U">VII. 21</ref>] and the least numbers measure those which have the same ratio with them the same number of times, the antecedent the antecedent and the consequent the consequent: [<ref target="elem.7.20" targOrder="U">VII. 20</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let it measure it according to <hi rend="ital">H</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">H</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>But further <hi rend="ital">A</hi> has also by multiplying itself made <hi rend="ital">B</hi>; [<ref target="elem.9.8" targOrder="U">IX. 8</ref>] therefore the product of <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">H</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, as <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to <hi rend="ital">H</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.19" targOrder="U">VII. 19</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> are prime, primes are also least, [<ref target="elem.7.21" targOrder="U">VII. 21</ref>] and the least measure those which have the same ratio the same number of times, the antecedent the antecedent and the consequent the consequent; [<ref target="elem.7.20" targOrder="U">VII. 20</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, as antecedent antecedent. </p>
      <p>But, again, it also does not measure it: which is impossible. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">A</hi> are not prime to one another. </p>
      <p>Therefore they are composite to one another. </p>
      <p>But numbers composite to one another are measured by some number. [<ref target="elem.7.def.14" targOrder="U">VII. Def. 14</ref>] </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is by hypothesis prime, and the prime is not measured by any number other than itself, therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, so that <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. </p>
      <p>[But it also measures <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>.] </p>
      <p>Similarly we can prove that, by however many prime numbers <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is measured, <hi rend="ital">A</hi> will also be measured by the same. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
