<div3 id="elem.12.14" n="14" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 14.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">Cones and cylinders which are on equal bases are to one another as their heights.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let <hi rend="ital">EB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FD</hi> be cylinders on equal bases, the circles <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>; I say that, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>, so is the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> be produced to the point <hi rend="ital">N</hi>, let <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> be made equal to the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, and let the cylinder <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> be conceived about <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> as axis. </p>
      <p>Since then the cylinders <hi rend="ital">EB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> are of the same height, they are to one another as their bases. [<ref target="elem.12.11" targOrder="U">XII. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the bases are equal to one another; therefore the cylinders <hi rend="ital">EB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> are also equal. </p>
      <p>And, since the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FM</hi> has been cut by the plane <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> which is parallel to its opposite planes, therefore, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>, so is the axis <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>. [<ref target="elem.12.13" targOrder="U">XII. 13</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the cylinder <hi rend="ital">CM</hi> is equal to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi>, and the axis <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>; therefore, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>, so is the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> to the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>, so is the cone <hi rend="ital">ABG</hi> to the cone <hi rend="ital">CDK</hi>. [<ref target="elem.12.10" targOrder="U">XII. 10</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore also, as the axis <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> is to the axis <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>, so is the cone <hi rend="ital">ABG</hi> to the cone <hi rend="ital">CDK</hi> and the cylinder <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> to the cylinder <hi rend="ital">FD</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
