<div3 id="elem.7.28" n="28" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 28.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If two numbers be prime to one another, the sum will also be prime to each of them; and, if the sum of two numbers be prime to any one of them, the original numbers will also be prime to one another.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let two numbers <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> prime to one another be added; I say that the sum <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is also prime to each of the numbers <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, if <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> are not prime to one another, some number will measure <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let a number measure them, and let it be <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Since then <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, therefore it will also measure the remainder <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it also measures <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> which are prime to one another: which is impossible. [<ref target="elem.7.def.12" targOrder="U">VII. Def. 12</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore no number will measure the numbers <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> are prime to one another. </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> are also prime to one another. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">CA</hi> is prime to each of the numbers <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>Again, let <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be prime to one another; I say that <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are also prime to one another. </p>
      <p>For, if <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are not prime to one another, some number will measure <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let a number measure them, and let it be <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures each of the numbers <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, it will also measure the whole <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it also measures <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> which are prime to one another: which is impossible. [<ref target="elem.7.def.12" targOrder="U">VII. Def. 12</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore no number will measure the numbers <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are prime to one another. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
