<div3 id="elem.9.8" n="8" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 8.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If as many numbers as we please beginning from an unit be in continued proportion, the third from the unit will be square, as will also those which successively leave out one; the fourth will be cube, as will also all those which leave out two; and the seventh will be at once cube and square, as will also those which leave out five.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let there be as many numbers as we please, <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, beginning from an unit and in continued proportion; I say that <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, the third from the unit, is square, as are also all those which leave out one; <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, the fourth, is cube, as are also all those which leave out two; and <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, the seventh, is at once cube and square, as are also all those which leave out five. </p>
      <p>For since, as the unit is to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, therefore the unit measures the number <hi rend="ital">A</hi> the same number of times that <hi rend="ital">A</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.def.20" targOrder="U">VII. Def. 20</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the unit measures the number <hi rend="ital">A</hi> according to the units in it; therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> also measures <hi rend="ital">B</hi> according to the units in <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying itself has made <hi rend="ital">B</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is square. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> are in continued proportion, and <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is square, therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is also square. [<ref target="elem.8.22" targOrder="U">VIII. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="ital">F</hi> is also square. </p>
      <p>Similarly we can prove that all those which leave out one are square. </p>
      <p>I say next that <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, the fourth from the unit, is cube, as are also all those which leave out two. </p>
      <p>For since, as the unit is to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">B</hi> to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, therefore the unit measures the number <hi rend="ital">A</hi> the same number of times that <hi rend="ital">B</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the unit measures the number <hi rend="ital">A</hi> according to the units in <hi rend="ital">A</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">B</hi> also measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi> according to the units in <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">B</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>Since then <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying itself has made <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, and by multiplying <hi rend="ital">B</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is cube. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi> are in continued proportion, and <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is cube, therefore <hi rend="ital">F</hi> is also cube. [<ref target="elem.8.23" targOrder="U">VIII. 23</ref>] </p>
      <p>But it was also proved square; therefore the seventh from the unit is both cube and square. </p>
      <p>Similarly we can prove that all the numbers which leave out five are also both cube and square. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
