<div3 id="elem.12.6" n="6" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 6.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">Pyramids which are of the same height and have polygonal bases are to one another as the bases.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let there be pyramids of the same height of which the polygons <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> are the bases and the points <hi rend="ital">M</hi>, <hi rend="ital">N</hi> the vertices; I say that, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHKLN</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FK</hi> be joined. </p>
      <p>Since then <hi rend="ital">ABCM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">ACDM</hi> are two pyramids which have triangular bases and equal height, they are to one another as the bases; [<ref target="elem.12.5" targOrder="U">XII. 5</ref>] therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ACD</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ACDM</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, <foreign lang="la">componendo</foreign>, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ACD</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ACDM</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.18" targOrder="U">V. 18</ref>] </p>
      <p>But also, as the base <hi rend="ital">ACD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ACDM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi>. [<ref target="elem.12.5" targOrder="U">XII. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore, <foreign lang="la">ex aequali</foreign>, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.22" targOrder="U">V. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>And again <foreign lang="la">componendo</foreign>, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.18" targOrder="U">V. 18</ref>] </p>
      <p>Similarly also it can be proved that, as the base <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHKLN</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi> are two pyramids which have triangular bases and equal height, therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi>. [<ref target="elem.12.5" targOrder="U">XII. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, as the base <hi rend="ital">ADE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi>, so was the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ADEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore also, <foreign lang="la">ex aequali</foreign>, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.22" targOrder="U">V. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>But further, as the base <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi>, so also was the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHN</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHKLN</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore also, <hi rend="ital">ex aequali</hi>, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCDEM</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">FGHKLN</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.22" targOrder="U">V. 22</ref>] Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
