<div3 id="elem.5.13" n="13" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 13.</head>
      <p><emph>If a first magnitude have to a second the same ratio as a third to a fourth</emph>, <emph>and the third have to the fourth a greater ratio than a fifth has to a sixth</emph>, <emph>the first will also have to the second a greater ratio than the fifth to the sixth</emph>. </p>
      <p>For let a first magnitude <emph>A</emph> have to a second <emph>B</emph> the same ratio as a third <emph>C</emph> has to a fourth <emph>D</emph>, and let the third <emph>C</emph> have to the fourth <emph>D</emph> a greater ratio than a fifth <emph>E</emph> has to a sixth <emph>F</emph>; I say that the first <emph>A</emph> will also have to the second <emph>B</emph> a greater ratio than the fifth <emph>E</emph> to the sixth <emph>F</emph>. </p>
      <p>For, since there are some equimultiples of <emph>C</emph>, <emph>E</emph>, and of <emph>D</emph>, <emph>F</emph> other, chance, equimultiples, such that the multiple of <emph>C</emph> is in excess of the multiple of <emph>D</emph>, <emph>E</emph> is not in excess of the multiple of <emph>F</emph>, [<ref target="elem.5.def.7" targOrder="U">V. Def. 7</ref>] let them be taken, and let <emph>G</emph>, <emph>H</emph> be equimultiples of <emph>C</emph>, <emph>E</emph>, and <emph>K</emph>, <emph>L</emph> other, chance, equimultiples of <emph>D</emph>, <emph>F</emph>, so that <emph>G</emph> is in excess of <emph>K</emph>, but <emph>H</emph> is not in excess of <emph>L</emph>; and, whatever multiple <emph>G</emph> is of <emph>C</emph>, let <emph>M</emph> be also that multiple of <emph>A</emph>, and, whatever multiple <emph>K</emph> is of <emph>D</emph>, let <emph>N</emph> be also that multiple of <emph>B</emph>. </p>
      <p>Now, since, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, so is <emph>C</emph> to <emph>D</emph>, and of <emph>A</emph>, <emph>C</emph> equimultiples <emph>M</emph>, <emph>G</emph> have been taken, and of <emph>B</emph>, <emph>D</emph> other, chance, equimultiples <emph>N</emph>, <emph>K</emph>, therefore, if <emph>M</emph> is in excess of <emph>N</emph>, <emph>G</emph> is also in excess of <emph>K</emph>, if equal, equal, and if less, less. [<ref target="elem.5.def.5" targOrder="U">V. Def. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <emph>G</emph> is in excess of <emph>K</emph>; therefore <emph>M</emph> is also in excess of <emph>N</emph>. </p>
      <p>But <emph>H</emph> is not in excess of <emph>L</emph>; and <emph>M</emph>, <emph>H</emph> are equimultiples of <emph>A</emph>, <emph>E</emph>, and <emph>N</emph>, <emph>L</emph> other, chance, equimultiples of <emph>B</emph>, <emph>F</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>A</emph> has to <emph>B</emph> a greater ratio than <emph>E</emph> has to <emph>F</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.7" targOrder="U">V. Def. 7</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
