<div3 id="elem.13.4" n="4" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 4.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If a straight line be cut in extreme and mean ratio</hi>, <hi rend="ital">the square on the whole and the square on the lesser segment together are triple of the square on the greater segment.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be a straight line, let it be cut in extreme and mean ratio at <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> be the greater segment; I say that the squares on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are triple of the square on <hi rend="ital">CA</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let the square <hi rend="ital">ADEB</hi> be described on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, and let the figure be drawn. </p>
      <p>Since then <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has been cut in extreme and mean ratio at <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is the greater segment, therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.def.3" targOrder="U">VI. Def. 3</ref>, <ref target="elem.6.17" targOrder="U">VI. 17</ref>] </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">HG</hi> the square on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">AF</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">FE</hi>, let <hi rend="ital">CK</hi> be added to each; therefore the whole <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is equal to the whole <hi rend="ital">CE</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CE</hi> are double of <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CE</hi> are the gnomon <hi rend="ital">LMN</hi> and the square <hi rend="ital">CK</hi>; therefore the gnomon <hi rend="ital">LMN</hi> and the square <hi rend="ital">CK</hi> are double of <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, further, <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> was also proved equal to <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>; therefore the gnomon <hi rend="ital">LMN</hi> and the squares <hi rend="ital">CK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HG</hi> are triple of the square <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>. </p>
      <p>And the gnomon <hi rend="ital">LMN</hi> and the squares <hi rend="ital">CK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HG</hi> are the whole square <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> and <hi rend="ital">CK</hi>, which are the squares on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, while <hi rend="ital">HG</hi> is the square on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the squares on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> are triple of the square on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
