<div3 id="elem.13.13" n="13" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 13.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">To construct a pyramid</hi>, <hi rend="ital">to comprehend it in a given sphere</hi>, <hi rend="ital">and to prove that the square on the diameter of the sphere is one and a half times the square on the side of the pyramid.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>Let the diameter <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> of the given sphere be set out, and let it be cut at the point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> so that <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is double of <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>; let the semicircle <hi rend="ital">ADB</hi> be described on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, let <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> be drawn from the point <hi rend="ital">C</hi> at right angles to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> be joined; let the circle <hi rend="ital">EFG</hi> which has its radius equal to <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> be set out, let the equilateral triangle <hi rend="ital">EFG</hi> be inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">EFG</hi>, [<ref target="elem.4.2" targOrder="U">IV. 2</ref>] let the centre of the circle, the point <hi rend="ital">H</hi>, be taken, [<ref target="elem.3.1" targOrder="U">III. 1</ref>] let <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HG</hi> be joined; from the point <hi rend="ital">H</hi> let <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> be set up at right angles to the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">EFG</hi>, [<ref target="elem.11.12" targOrder="U">XI. 12</ref>] let <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> equal to the straight line <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> be cut off from <hi rend="ital">HK</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">KE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KG</hi> be joined. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> is at right angles to the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">EFG</hi>, therefore it will also make right angles with all the straight lines which meet it and are in the plane of the circle <hi rend="ital">EFG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.11.def.3" targOrder="U">XI. Def. 3</ref>] </p>
      <p>But each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">HE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HG</hi> meets it: therefore <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> is at right angles to each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">HE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">HK</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> to <hi rend="ital">HE</hi>, and they contain right angles, therefore the base <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> is equal to the base <hi rend="ital">KE</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.4" targOrder="U">I. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>For the same reason each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">KF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KG</hi> is also equal to <hi rend="ital">DA</hi>; therefore the three straight lines <hi rend="ital">KE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KG</hi> are equal to one another. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is double of <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is triple of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>, as will be proved afterwards. </p>
      <p>Therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is triple of the square on <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">FE</hi> is also triple of the square on <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>, [<ref target="elem.13.12" targOrder="U">XIII. 12</ref>] and <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> is also equal to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> was proved equal to each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">KE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KG</hi>; therefore each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GE</hi> is also equal to each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">KE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KG</hi>; therefore the four triangles <hi rend="ital">EFG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KEF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KFG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KEG</hi> are equilateral. </p>
      <p>Therefore a pyramid has been constructed out of four equilateral triangles, the triangle <hi rend="ital">EFG</hi> being its base and the point <hi rend="ital">K</hi> its vertex. </p>
      <p>It is next required to comprehend it in the given sphere and to prove that the square on the diameter of the sphere is one and a half times the square on the side of the pyramid. </p>
      <p>For let the straight line <hi rend="ital">HL</hi> be produced in a straight line with <hi rend="ital">KH</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">HL</hi> be made equal to <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now, since, as <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> to <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, [<ref target="elem.6.8.p.1" targOrder="U">VI. 8, Por.</ref>] while <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">KH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> to <hi rend="ital">HE</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> to <hi rend="ital">HL</hi>, therefore, as <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">HE</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> to <hi rend="ital">HL</hi>; therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">KH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HL</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.17" targOrder="U">VI. 17</ref>] </p>
      <p>And each of the angles <hi rend="ital">KHE</hi>. <hi rend="ital">EHL</hi> is right; therefore the semicircle described on <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> will pass through <hi rend="ital">E</hi> also. [cf. <ref target="elem.6.8" targOrder="U">VI. 8</ref>, <ref target="elem.3.31" targOrder="U">III. 31</ref>.] </p>
      <p>If then, <hi rend="ital">KL</hi> remaining fixed, the semicircle be carried round and restored to the same position from which it began to be moved, it will also pass through the points <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, <hi rend="ital">G</hi>, since, if <hi rend="ital">FL</hi>, <hi rend="ital">LG</hi> be joined, the angles at <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, <hi rend="ital">G</hi> similarly become right angles; and the pyramid will be comprehended in the given sphere. </p>
      <p>For <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>, the diameter of the sphere, is equal to the diameter <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> of the given sphere, inasmuch as <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> was made equal to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">HL</hi> to <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. </p>
      <p>I say next that the square on the diameter of the sphere is one and a half times the square on the side of the pyramid </p>
      <p>For, since <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is double of <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is triple of <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>; and, <foreign lang="la">convertendo</foreign>, <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is one and a half times <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is also one and a half times the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>. </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is the diameter of the given sphere, and <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is equal to the side of the pyramid. </p>
      <p>Therefore the square on the diameter of the sphere is one and a half times the square on the side of the pyramid. Q. E. D.</p>
      <div4 id="elem.13.13.l.1" type="lemma">
       <head>LEMMA.</head>
       <p>It is to be proved that, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>. </p>
       <p>For let the figure of the semicircle be set out, let <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> be joined, let the square <hi rend="ital">EC</hi> be described on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, and let the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">FB</hi> be completed. </p>
       <p>Since then, because the triangle <hi rend="ital">DAB</hi> is equiangular with the triangle <hi rend="ital">DAC</hi>, as <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">DA</hi> to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, [<ref target="elem.6.8" targOrder="U">VI. 8</ref>, <ref target="elem.6.4" targOrder="U">VI. 4</ref>] <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.17" targOrder="U">VI. 17</ref>] </p>
       <p>And since, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> to <hi rend="ital">BF</hi>, [<ref target="elem.6.1" targOrder="U">VI. 1</ref>] and <hi rend="ital">EB</hi> is the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, for <hi rend="ital">EA</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">BF</hi> is the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, therefore, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. </p>
       <p>And the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi>, and the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>, for the perpendicular <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> is a mean proportional between the segments <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> of the base, because the angle <hi rend="ital">ADB</hi> is right. [<ref target="elem.6.8.p.1" targOrder="U">VI. 8, Por.</ref>] </p>
       <p>Therefore, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
      </div4>
     </div3>
     
