<div3 id="elem.10.22" n="22" type="propositions i&#x2014;47">
      <head>PROPOSITION 22.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">The square on a medial straight line, if applied to a rational straight line, produces as breadth a straight line rational and incommensurable in length with that to which it is applied</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">A</hi> be medial and <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> rational, and let a rectangular area <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> be applied to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, producing <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> as breadth; I say that <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is rational and incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, since <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is medial, the square on it is equal to a rectangular area contained by rational straight lines commensurable in square only. [<ref target="elem.10.21" targOrder="U">X. 21</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let the square on it be equal to <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the square on it is also equal to <hi rend="ital">BD</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it is also equiangular with it; and in equal and equiangular parallelograms the sides about the equal angles are reciprocally proportional; [<ref target="elem.6.14" targOrder="U">VI. 14</ref>] therefore, proportionally, as <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore also, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.22" targOrder="U">VI. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> is commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, for each of these straight lines is rational; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is also commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.11" targOrder="U">X. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is rational; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is also rational; [<ref target="elem.10.def.4" targOrder="U">X. Def. 4</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is rational. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, for they are commensurable in square only, and, as <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">FE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, [Lemma] therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is incommensurable with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">FE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.11" targOrder="U">X. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the square on <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, for the straight lines are rational in square; and the rectangle <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> is commensurable with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">FE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, for they are equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi>; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is also incommensurable with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.13" targOrder="U">X. 13</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, as the square on <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> to <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>; [Lemma] therefore <hi rend="ital">DC</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.11" targOrder="U">X. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is rational and incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
