<div3 id="elem.5.21" n="21" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 21.</head>
      <p><emph>If there be three magnitudes</emph>, <emph>and others equal to them in multitude</emph>, <emph>which taken two and two together are in the same ratio</emph>, <emph>and the proportion of them be perturbed</emph>, <emph>then</emph>, <emph>if</emph><foreign lang="la"> ex aequali</foreign>
       <emph>the first magnitude is greater than the third</emph>, <emph>the fourth will also be greater than the sixth; if equal</emph>, <emph>equal; and if less</emph>, <emph>less</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let there be three magnitudes <emph>A</emph>, <emph>B</emph>, <emph>C</emph>, and others <emph>D</emph>, <emph>E</emph>, <emph>F</emph> equal to them in multitude, which taken two and two are in the same ratio, and let the proportion of them be perturbed, so that, <hi rend="center">as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, so is <emph>E</emph> to <emph>F</emph>,</hi> and, as <emph>B</emph> is to <emph>C</emph>, so is <emph>D</emph> to <emph>E</emph>, and let <emph>A</emph> be greater than <emph>C</emph>
       <foreign lang="la">ex aequali</foreign>; I say that <emph>D</emph> will also be greater than <emph>F</emph>; if <emph>A</emph> is equal to <emph>C</emph>, equal; and if less, less. </p>
      <p>For, since <emph>A</emph> is greater than <emph>C</emph>, and <emph>B</emph> is some other magnitude, therefore <emph>A</emph> has to <emph>B</emph> a greater ratio than <emph>C</emph> has to <emph>B</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.8" targOrder="U">V. 8</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, so is <emph>E</emph> to <emph>F</emph>, and, as <emph>C</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, inversely, so is <emph>E</emph> to <emph>D</emph>. Therefore also <emph>E</emph> has to <emph>F</emph> a greater ratio than <emph>E</emph> has to <emph>D</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.13" targOrder="U">V. 13</ref>] </p>
      <p>But that to which the same has a greater ratio is less; [<ref target="elem.5.10" targOrder="U">V. 10</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>F</emph> is less than <emph>D</emph>; therefore <emph>D</emph> is greater than <emph>F</emph>.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>Similarly we can prove that, <hi rend="center">if <emph>A</emph> be equal to <emph>C</emph>, <emph>D</emph> will also be equal to <emph>F</emph>;</hi> and if less, less. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
