<div3 id="elem.10.31" n="31" type="propositions i&#x2014;47">
      <head>PROPOSITION 31.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">To find two medial straight lines commensurable in square only, containing a rational rectangle, and such that the square on the greater is greater than the square on the less by the square on a straight line commensurable in length with the greater.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let there be set out two rational straight lines <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> commensurable in square only and such that the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, being the greater, is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi> the less by the square on a straight line commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.29" targOrder="U">X. 29</ref>] </p>
      <p>And let the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> be equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now the rectangle <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is medial; [<ref target="elem.10.21" targOrder="U">X. 21</ref>] therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is also medial; therefore <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is also medial. [<ref target="elem.10.21" targOrder="U">X. 21</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let the rectangle <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> be equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is rational; therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is also rational. </p>
      <p>And since, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, so is the rectangle <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, while the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is equal to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, and the rectangle <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, therefore, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">C</hi> to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; therefore also, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">C</hi> to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is commensurable with <hi rend="ital">B</hi> in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is also commensurable with <hi rend="ital">D</hi> in square only. [<ref target="elem.10.11" targOrder="U">X. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is medial; therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> is also medial. [<ref target="elem.10.23" targOrder="U">X. 23</ref>, addition] </p>
      <p>And since, as <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">C</hi> to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, and the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, therefore also the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.14" targOrder="U">X. 14</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore two medial straight lines <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, commensurable in square only and containing a rational rectangle, have been found, and the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>Similarly also it can be proved that the square on <hi rend="ital">C</hi> exceeds the square on <hi rend="ital">D</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, when the square on <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">B</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.30" targOrder="U">X. 30</ref>]</p>
     </div3>
     
