<div3 id="elem.1.34" n="34" type="proposition">
      <head>Proposition 34.</head>
      <div4 type="Enunc">
       <p>In parallelogrammic areas the opposite sides and angles are equal to one another, and the diameter bisects the areas.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 type="Proof">
       <p>Let <emph>ACDB</emph> be a parallelogrammic area, and <emph>BC</emph> its diameter; <emph>ACDB</emph> are equal to one another, and the diameter <emph>BC</emph> bisects it. </p>
       <p>For, since <emph>AB</emph> is parallel to <emph>CD</emph>, and the straight line <emph>BC</emph> has fallen <hi rend="center">the alternate angles <emph>ABC</emph>, <emph>BCD</emph> are equal to one another. [<ref target="elem.1.29" targOrder="U">I. 29</ref>]</hi></p>
       <p>Again, since <emph>AC</emph> is parallel to <emph>BD</emph>, and <emph>BC</emph>has fallen upon them, <hi rend="center">the alternate angles <emph>ACB</emph>, <emph>CBD</emph> are equal to one another. [<ref target="elem.1.29" targOrder="U">I. 29</ref>]</hi></p>
       <p>Therefore <emph>ABC</emph>, <emph>DCB</emph> are two triangles having the two angles <emph>ABC</emph>, <emph>BCA</emph> equal to the two angles <emph>DCB</emph>, <emph>CBD</emph> respectively, and one side equal to one side, namely that <emph>BC</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore they will also have the remaining sides equal to the remaining sides respectively, and the remaining angle to the remaining angle; [<ref target="elem.1.26" targOrder="U">I. 26</ref>] therefore the side <emph>AB</emph> is equal to <emph>CD</emph>, <emph>AC</emph> to <emph>BD</emph>,</hi> and further the angle <emph>BAC</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>CDB</emph>.</p>
       <p>And, since the angle <emph>ABC</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>BCD</emph>, <hi rend="center">and the angle <emph>CBD</emph> to the angle <emph>ACB</emph>, the whole angle <emph>ABD</emph> is equal to the whole angle <emph>ACD</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.c.n.2" targOrder="U">C.N. 2</ref>]</hi>
        <emph>BAC</emph> was also proved equal to the angle <emph>CDB</emph>.</p>
       <p>Therefore in parallelogrammic areas the opposite sides and angles are equal to one another.</p>
       <p>I say, next, that the diameter also bisects the areas.</p>
       <p>For, since <emph>AB</emph> is equal to <emph>CD</emph>, <emph>BC</emph> is common, the two sides <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BC</emph> are equal to the two sides <emph>DC</emph>, <emph>CB</emph> respectively; <hi rend="center">and the angle <emph>ABC</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>BCD</emph>; therefore the base <emph>AC</emph> is also equal to <emph>DB</emph>, <emph>ABC</emph> is equal to the triangle <emph>DCB</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.4" targOrder="U">I. 4</ref>]</hi></p>
       <p>Therefore the diameter <emph>BC</emph> bisects the parallelogram <emph>ACDB</emph>.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 type="QED">
       <p>Q. E. D.</p>
      </div4>
      <note n="1" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p>It is to be observed that, when parallelograms have to be mentioned for the first time, Euclid calls them <quote>parallelogrammic areas</quote>
 or, more exactly, <quote>parallelogram</quote>
 areas (<foreign lang="greek">παραλληλόγραμμα χωρία</foreign>). The meaning is simply areas bounded by parallel straight lines with the further limitation placed upon the term by Euclid that only <emph>four-sided</emph> figures are so called, although of course there are certain regular polygons which have opposite sides parallel, and which therefore might be said to be areas bounded by parallel straight lines. We gather from Proclus (<xref n="Proc. p. 393" from="ROOT" to="DITTO" targOrder="U">p. 393</xref>) that the word <quote>parallelogram</quote>
 was first introduced by Euclid, that its use was suggested by <ref target="elem.1.33" targOrder="U">I. 33</ref>, and that the formation of the word <foreign lang="greek">παραλληλόγραμμος</foreign> (parallel-lined) was analogous to that of <foreign lang="greek">εὐθύγραμμος</foreign> (straight-lined or rectilineal).</p>
      </note>
      <note n="17, 18, 40. DCB" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p>and 36. <hi rend="bold">DC, CB</hi>. The Greek has in these places <quote><emph>BCD</emph></quote>
 and <quote><emph>CD</emph>, <emph>BC</emph></quote>
 respectively. Cf. note on <ref target="elem.1.33" targOrder="U">I. 33</ref>, lines 15, 18.</p>
      </note>
     </div3>
     
