<div3 id="elem.10.52" n="52" type="propositions 48&#x2014;84">
      <head>PROPOSITION 52.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">To find the fifth binomial straight line</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let two numbers <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> be set out such that <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has not to either of them the ratio which a square number has to a square number; let any rational straight line <hi rend="ital">D</hi> be set out, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> be commensurable with <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is rational. </p>
      <p>Let it be contrived that, as <hi rend="ital">CA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.6.p.1" targOrder="U">X. 6, Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">CA</hi> has not to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore neither has the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is binomial. [<ref target="elem.10.36" targOrder="U">X. 36</ref>] </p>
      <p>I say next that it is also a fifth binomial straight line. </p>
      <p>For since, as <hi rend="ital">CA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, inversely, as <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">FE</hi>; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">GF</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">FE</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let then the squares on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">H</hi> be equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>; therefore, <foreign lang="la">convertendo</foreign>, as the number <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">GF</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">H</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.19.p.1" targOrder="U">V. 19, Por.</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has not to <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number; therefore neither has the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the ratio which a square number has to a square number. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">H</hi>; [<ref target="elem.10.9" targOrder="U">X. 9</ref>] so that the square on <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">FE</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>. </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FE</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only, and the lesser term <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is commensurable in length with the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">D</hi> set out. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is a fifth binomial straight line. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
