<div3 id="elem.5.8" n="8" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 8.</head>
      <p><emph>Of unequal magnitudes</emph>, <emph>the greater has to the same a greater ratio than the less has</emph>; <emph>and the same has to the less a greater ratio than it has to the greater</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>C</emph> be unequal magnitudes, and let <emph>AB</emph> be greater; let <emph>D</emph> be another, chance, magnitude; I say that <emph>AB</emph> has to <emph>D</emph> a greater ratio than <emph>C</emph> has to <emph>D</emph>, and <emph>D</emph> has to <emph>C</emph> a greater ratio than it has to <emph>AB</emph>. </p>
      <p>For, since <emph>AB</emph> is greater than <emph>C</emph>, let <emph>BE</emph> be made equal to <emph>C</emph>; then the less of the magnitudes <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EB</emph>, if multiplied, will sometime be greater than <emph>D</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.4" targOrder="U">V. Def. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>[<title>Case</title> I.] </p>
      <p>First, let <emph>AE</emph> be less than <emph>EB</emph>; let <emph>AE</emph> be multiplied, and let <emph>FG</emph> be a multiple of it which is greater than <emph>D</emph>; then, whatever multiple <emph>FG</emph> is of <emph>AE</emph>, let <emph>GH</emph> be made the same multiple of <emph>EB</emph> and <emph>K</emph> of <emph>C</emph>; and let <emph>L</emph> be taken double of <emph>D</emph>, <emph>M</emph> triple of it, and successive multiples increasing by one, until what is taken is a multiple of <emph>D</emph> and the first that is greater than <emph>K</emph>. Let it be taken, and let it be <emph>N</emph> which is quadruple of <emph>D</emph> and the first multiple of it that is greather than <emph>K</emph>. </p>
      <p>Then, since <emph>K</emph> is less than <emph>N</emph> first, therefore <emph>K</emph> is not less than <emph>M</emph>. </p>
      <p>And, since <emph>FG</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>AE</emph> that <emph>GH</emph> is of <emph>EB</emph>, therefore <emph>FG</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>AE</emph> that <emph>FH</emph> is of <emph>AB</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.1" targOrder="U">V. 1</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <emph>FG</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>AE</emph> that <emph>K</emph> is of <emph>C</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>FH</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>AB</emph> that <emph>K</emph> is of <emph>C</emph>; therefore <emph>FH</emph>, <emph>K</emph> are equimultiples of <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>C</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Again, since <emph>GH</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>EB</emph> that <emph>K</emph> is of <emph>C</emph>, and <emph>EB</emph> is equal to <emph>C</emph>, <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>GH</emph> is equal to <emph>K</emph>.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>But <emph>K</emph> is not less than <emph>M</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore neither is <emph>GH</emph> less than <emph>M</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And <emph>FG</emph> is greater than <emph>D</emph>; therefore the whole <emph>FH</emph> is greater than <emph>D</emph>, <emph>M</emph> together. </p>
      <p>But <emph>D</emph>, <emph>M</emph> together are equal to <emph>N</emph>, inasmuch as <emph>M</emph> is triple of <emph>D</emph>, and <emph>M</emph>, <emph>D</emph> together are quadruple of <emph>D</emph>, while <emph>N</emph> is also quadruple of <emph>D</emph>; whence <emph>M</emph>, <emph>D</emph> together are equal to <emph>N</emph>. </p>
      <p>But <emph>FH</emph> is greater than <emph>M</emph>, <emph>D</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>FH</emph> is in excess of <emph>N</emph>,</hi> while <emph>K</emph> is not in excess of <emph>N</emph>. </p>
      <p>And <emph>FH</emph>, <emph>K</emph> are equimultiples of <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>C</emph>, while <emph>N</emph> is another, chance, multiple of <emph>D</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>AB</emph> has to <emph>D</emph> a greater ratio than <emph>C</emph> has to <emph>D</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.7" targOrder="U">V. Def. 7</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>I say next, that <emph>D</emph> also has to <emph>C</emph> a greater ratio than <emph>D</emph> has to <emph>AB</emph>. </p>
      <p>For, with the same construction, we can prove similarly that <emph>N</emph> is in excess of <emph>K</emph>, while <emph>N</emph> is not in excess of <emph>FH</emph>. </p>
      <p>And <emph>N</emph> is a multiple of <emph>D</emph>, while <emph>FH</emph>, <emph>K</emph> are other, chance, equimultiples of <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>C</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>D</emph> has to <emph>C</emph> a greater ratio than <emph>D</emph> has to <emph>AB</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.7" targOrder="U">V. Def. 7</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>[<title>Case</title> 2.] </p>
      <p>Again, let <emph>AE</emph> be greater than <emph>EB</emph>. </p>
      <p>Then the less, <emph>EB</emph>, if multiplied, will sometime be greater than <emph>D</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.4" targOrder="U">V. Def. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let it be multiplied, and let <emph>GH</emph> be a multiple of <emph>EB</emph> and greater than <emph>D</emph>; and, whatever multiple <emph>GH</emph> is of <emph>EB</emph>, let <emph>FG</emph> be made the same multiple of <emph>AE</emph>, and <emph>K</emph>
       <emph>C</emph>. </p>
      <p>Then we can prove similarly that <emph>FH</emph>, <emph>K</emph> are equimultiples of <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>C</emph>; and, similarly, let <emph>N</emph> be taken a multiple of <emph>D</emph> but the first that is greater than <emph>FG</emph>, so that <emph>FG</emph> is again not less than <emph>M</emph>. </p>
      <p>But <emph>GH</emph> is greater than <emph>D</emph>; therefore the whole <emph>FH</emph> is in excess of <emph>D</emph>, <emph>M</emph>, that is, of <emph>N</emph>. </p>
      <p>Now <emph>K</emph> is not in excess of <emph>N</emph>, inasmuch as <emph>FG</emph> also, which is greater than <emph>GH</emph>, that is, than <emph>K</emph>, is not in excess of <emph>N</emph>. </p>
      <p>And in the same manner, by following the above argument, we complete the demonstration. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
