<div3 id="elem.4.12" n="12" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 12.</head>
      <p><emph>About a given circle to circumscribe an equilateral and equiangular pentagon</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>ABCDE</emph> be the given circle; thus it is required to circumscribe an equilateral and equiangular pentagon about the circle <emph>ABCDE</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>A</emph>, <emph>B</emph>, <emph>C</emph>, <emph>D</emph>, <emph>E</emph> be conceived to be the angular points of the inscribed pentagon, so that the circumferences <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BC</emph>, <emph>CD</emph>, <emph>DE</emph>, <emph>EA</emph> are equal; [<ref target="elem.4.11" targOrder="U">IV. 11</ref>] <emph>A</emph>, <emph>B</emph>, <emph>C</emph>, <emph>D</emph>, <emph>E</emph> let <emph>GH</emph>, <emph>HK</emph>, <emph>KL</emph>, <emph>LM</emph>, <emph>MG</emph> be drawn touching the circle; [<ref target="elem.3.16.p.1" targOrder="U">III. 16, Por.</ref>] let the centre <emph>F</emph> of the circle <emph>ABCDE</emph> be taken [<ref target="elem.3.1" targOrder="U">III. 1</ref>], and let <emph>FB</emph>, <emph>FK</emph>, <emph>FC</emph>, <emph>FL</emph>, <emph>FD</emph> be joined. </p>
      <p>Then, since the straight line <emph>KL</emph> touches the circle <emph>ABCDE</emph> at <emph>C</emph>, and <emph>FC</emph> has been joined from the centre <emph>F</emph> to the point of contact at <emph>C</emph>, <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>FC</emph> is perpendicular to <emph>KL</emph>; [<ref target="elem.3.18" targOrder="U">III. 18</ref>] therefore each of the angles at <emph>C</emph> is right.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="center">the angles at the points <emph>B</emph>, <emph>D</emph> are also right.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>And, since the angle <emph>FCK</emph> is right, therefore the square on <emph>FK</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>FC</emph>, <emph>CK</emph>. </p>
      <p>For the same reason [<ref target="elem.1.47" targOrder="U">I. 47</ref>] <hi rend="center">the square on <emph>FK</emph> is also equal to the squares on <emph>FB</emph>, <emph>BK</emph>; so that the squares on <emph>FC</emph>, <emph>CK</emph> are equal to the squares on <emph>FB</emph>, <emph>BK</emph>, of which the square on <emph>FC</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>FB</emph>;</hi> therefore the square on <emph>CK</emph> which remains is equal to the square on <emph>BK</emph>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <emph>BK</emph> is equal to <emph>CK</emph>. </p>
      <p>And, since <emph>FB</emph> is equal to <emph>FC</emph>, and <emph>FK</emph> common, <hi rend="center">the two sides <emph>BF</emph>, <emph>FK</emph> are equal to the two sides <emph>CF</emph>, <emph>FK</emph>; and the base <emph>BK</emph> equal to the base <emph>CK</emph>; therefore the angle <emph>BFK</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>KFC</emph>, [<ref target="elem.1.8" targOrder="U">I. 8</ref>] and the angle <emph>BKF</emph> to the angle <emph>FKC</emph>.</hi> Therefore the angle <emph>BFC</emph> is double of the angle <emph>KFC</emph>, <hi rend="center">and the angle <emph>BKC</emph> of the angle <emph>FKC</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="center">the angle <emph>CFD</emph> is also double of the angle <emph>CFL</emph>, and the angle <emph>DLC</emph> of the angle <emph>FLC</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Now, since the circumference <emph>BC</emph> is equal to <emph>CD</emph>, the angle <emph>BFC</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>CFD</emph>. [<ref target="elem.3.27" targOrder="U">III. 27</ref>] </p>
      <p>And the angle <emph>BFC</emph> is double of the angle <emph>KFC</emph>, and the angle <emph>DFC</emph> of the angle <emph>LFC</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the angle <emph>KFC</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>LFC</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But the angle <emph>FCK</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>FCL</emph>; therefore <emph>FKC</emph>, <emph>FLC</emph> are two triangles having two angles equal to two angles and one side equal to one side, namely <emph>FC</emph> which is common to them; therefore they will also have the remaining sides equal to the remaining sides, and the remaining angle to the remaining angle; [<ref target="elem.1.26" targOrder="U">I. 26</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore the straight line <emph>KC</emph> is equal to <emph>CL</emph>, and the angle <emph>FKC</emph> to the angle <emph>FLC</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And, since <emph>KC</emph> is equal to <emph>CL</emph>, therefore <emph>KL</emph> is double of <emph>KC</emph>. </p>
      <p>For the same reason it can be proved that <hi rend="center"><emph>HK</emph> is also double of <emph>BK</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And <emph>BK</emph> is equal to <emph>KC</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>HK</emph> is also equal to <emph>KL</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Similarly each of the straight lines <emph>HG</emph>, <emph>GM</emph>, <emph>ML</emph> can also be proved equal to each of the straight lines <emph>HK</emph>, <emph>KL</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the pentagon <emph>GHKLM</emph> is equilateral.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>I say next that it is also equiangular. </p>
      <p>For, since the angle <emph>FKC</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>FLC</emph>, and the angle <emph>HKL</emph> was proved double of the angle <emph>FKC</emph>, <hi rend="center">and the angle <emph>KLM</emph> double of the angle <emph>FLC</emph>, therefore the angle <emph>HKL</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>KLM</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Similarly each of the angles <emph>KHG</emph>, <emph>HGM</emph>, <emph>GML</emph> can also be proved equal to each of the angles <emph>HKL</emph>, <emph>KLM</emph>; therefore the five angles <emph>GHK</emph>, <emph>HKL</emph>, <emph>KLM</emph>, <emph>LMG</emph>, <emph>MGH</emph> are equal to one another. </p>
      <p>Therefore the pentagon <emph>GHKLM</emph> is equiangular. </p>
      <p>And it was also proved equilateral; and it has been circumscribed about the circle <emph>ABCDE</emph>. Q. E. F.</p>
     </div3>
     
