<div3 id="elem.12.4" n="4" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 4.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If there be two pyramids of the same height which have triangular bases</hi>, <hi rend="ital">and cach of them be divided into two pyramids equal to one another and similar to the whole, and into two equal prisms</hi>, <hi rend="ital">then</hi>, <hi rend="ital">as the base of the one pyramid is to the base of the other pyramid</hi>, <hi rend="ital">so will all the prisms in the one pyramid be to all the prisms</hi>, <hi rend="ital">being equal in multitude</hi>, <hi rend="ital">in the other pyramid.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let there be two pyramids of the same height which have the triangular bases <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, and vertices the points <hi rend="ital">G</hi>, <hi rend="ital">H</hi>, and let each of them be divided into two pyramids equal to one another and similar to the whole and into two equal prisms; [<ref target="elem.12.3" targOrder="U">XII. 3</ref>] I say that, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so are all the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to all the prisms, being equal in multitude, in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>, </p>
      <p>For, since <hi rend="ital">BO</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">OC</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> to <hi rend="ital">LC</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">LO</hi> is parallel to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, and the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi>. </p>
      <p>For the same reason the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> is also similar to the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is double of <hi rend="ital">CO</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> of <hi rend="ital">FV</hi>, therefore, as <hi rend="ital">BC</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CO</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">FV</hi>. </p>
      <p>And on <hi rend="ital">BC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CO</hi> are described the similar and similarly situated rectilineal figures <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi>, and on <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FV</hi> the similar and similarly situated figures <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi>; therefore, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi>, so is the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> to the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi>; [<ref target="elem.6.22" targOrder="U">VI. 22</ref>] therefore, alternately, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so is the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> to the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.16" targOrder="U">V. 16</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi>, so is the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> its opposite to the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> its opposite; [Lemma following] therefore also, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so is the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> its opposite to the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> its opposite. </p>
      <p>But, as the said prisms are to one another, so is the prism in which the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">KBOL</hi> is the base and the straight line <hi rend="ital">PM</hi> its opposite to the prism in which the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">QEVR</hi> is the base and the straight line <hi rend="ital">ST</hi> its opposite. [<ref target="elem.11.39" targOrder="U">XI. 39</ref>; cf. <ref target="elem.12.3" targOrder="U">XII. 3</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore also the two prisms, that in which the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">KBOL</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PM</hi> its opposite, and that in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> its opposite, are to the prisms in which <hi rend="ital">QEVR</hi> is the base and the straight line <hi rend="ital">ST</hi> its opposite and in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> its opposite in the same ratio [<ref target="elem.5.12" targOrder="U">V. 12</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore also, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so are the said two prisms to the said two prisms. </p>
      <p>And similarly, if the pyramids <hi rend="ital">PMNG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">STUH</hi> be divided into two prisms and two pyramids, as the base <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">STU</hi>, so will the two prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">PMNG</hi> be to the two prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">STUH</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as the base <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">STU</hi>, so is the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>; for the triangles <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi>, <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> are equal to the triangles <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> respectively. </p>
      <p>Therefore also, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so are the four prisms to the four prisms. </p>
      <p>And similarly also, if we divide the remaining pyramids into two pyramids and into two prisms, then, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so will all the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> be to all the prisms, being equal in multitude, in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
      <div4 id="elem.12.4.l.1" type="lemma">
       <head>LEMMA.</head>
       <p>But that, as the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is to the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi>, so is the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> its opposite to the prism in which the triangle <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> is the base and <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> its opposite, we must prove as follows. </p>
       <p>For in the same figure let perpendiculars be conceived drawn from <hi rend="ital">G</hi>, <hi rend="ital">H</hi> to the planes <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>; these are of course equal because, by hypothesis, the pyramids are of equal height. </p>
       <p>Now, since the two straight lines <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> and the perpendicular from <hi rend="ital">G</hi> are cut by the parallel planes <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi>, they will be cut in the same ratios. [<ref target="elem.11.17" targOrder="U">XI. 17</ref>] </p>
       <p>And <hi rend="ital">GC</hi> is bisected by the plane <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi> at <hi rend="ital">N</hi>; therefore the perpendicular from <hi rend="ital">G</hi> to the plane <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> will also be bisected by the plane <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi>. </p>
       <p>For the same reason the perpendicular from <hi rend="ital">H</hi> to the plane <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> will also be bisected by the plane <hi rend="ital">STU</hi>. </p>
       <p>And the perpendiculars from <hi rend="ital">G</hi>, <hi rend="ital">H</hi> to the planes <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> are equal; therefore the perpendiculars from the triangles <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi>, <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> to the planes <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> are also equal. </p>
       <p>Therefore the prisms in which the triangles <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi> are bases, and <hi rend="ital">PMN</hi>, <hi rend="ital">STU</hi> their opposites, are of equal height. </p>
       <p>Hence also the parallelepipedal solids described from the said prisms are of equal height and are to one another as their bases; [<ref target="elem.11.32" targOrder="U">XI. 32</ref>] therefore their halves, namely the said prisms, are to one another as the base <hi rend="ital">LOC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">RVF</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
      </div4>
     </div3>
     
