<div3 id="elem.4.10" n="10" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 10.</head>
      <p><emph>To construct an isosceles triangle having each of the angles at the base double of the remaining one</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let any straight line <emph>AB</emph> be set out, and let it be cut at the point <emph>C</emph> so that the rectangle contained by <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BC</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>CA</emph>; [<ref target="elem.2.11" targOrder="U">II. 11</ref>] with centre <emph>A</emph> and distance <emph>AB</emph> let the circle <emph>BDE</emph> be described, and let there be fitted in the circle <emph>BDE</emph> the straight line <emph>BD</emph> equal to the straight line <emph>AC</emph> which is not greater than the diameter of the circle <emph>BDE</emph>. [<ref target="elem.4.1" targOrder="U">IV. 1</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let <emph>AD</emph>, <emph>DC</emph> be joined, and let the circle <emph>ACD</emph> be circumscribed about the triangle <emph>ACD</emph>. [<ref target="elem.4.5" targOrder="U">IV. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>Then, since the rectangle <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BC</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>AC</emph>, and <emph>AC</emph> is equal to <emph>BD</emph>, therefore the rectangle <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BC</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>BD</emph>. </p>
      <p>And, since a point <emph>B</emph> has been taken outside the circle <emph>ACD</emph>, and from <emph>B</emph> the two straight lines <emph>BA</emph>, <emph>BD</emph> have fallen on the circle <emph>ACD</emph>, and one of them cuts it, while the other falls on it, and the rectangle <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BC</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>BD</emph>, <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>BD</emph> touches the circle <emph>ACD</emph>. [<ref target="elem.3.37" targOrder="U">III. 37</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Since, then, <emph>BD</emph> touches it, and <emph>DC</emph> is drawn across from the point of contact at <emph>D</emph>, therefore the angle <emph>BDC</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>DAC</emph> in the alternate segment of the circle. [<ref target="elem.3.32" targOrder="U">III. 32</ref>] </p>
      <p>Since, then, the angle <emph>BDC</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>DAC</emph>, let the angle <emph>CDA</emph> be added to each; therefore the whole angle <emph>BDA</emph> is equal to the two angles <emph>CDA</emph>, <emph>DAC</emph>. </p>
      <p>But the exterior angle <emph>BCD</emph> is equal to the angles <emph>CDA</emph>, <emph>DAC</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.32" targOrder="U">I. 32</ref>] therefore the angle <emph>BDA</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>BCD</emph>. </p>
      <p>But the angle <emph>BDA</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>CBD</emph>, since the side <emph>AD</emph> is also equal to <emph>AB</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.5" targOrder="U">I. 5</ref>] so that the angle <emph>DBA</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>BCD</emph>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the three angles <emph>BDA</emph>, <emph>DBA</emph>, <emph>BCD</emph> are equal to one another. </p>
      <p>And, since the angle <emph>DBC</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>BCD</emph>, <hi rend="center">the side <emph>BD</emph> is also equal to the side <emph>DC</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.6" targOrder="U">I. 6</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>But <emph>BD</emph> is by hypothesis equal to <emph>CA</emph>; therefore <emph>CA</emph> is also equal to <emph>CD</emph>, <hi rend="center">so that the angle <emph>CDA</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>DAC</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.5" targOrder="U">I. 5</ref>]</hi> therefore the angles <emph>CDA</emph>, <emph>DAC</emph> are double of the angle <emph>DAC</emph>. </p>
      <p>But the angle <emph>BCD</emph> is equal to the angles <emph>CDA</emph>, <emph>DAC</emph>; therefore the angle <emph>BCD</emph> is also double of the angle <emph>CAD</emph>. </p>
      <p>But the angle <emph>BCD</emph> is equal to each of the angles <emph>BDA</emph>, <emph>DBA</emph>; therefore each of the angles <emph>BDA</emph>, <emph>DBA</emph> is also double of the angle <emph>DAB</emph>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the isosceles triangle <emph>ABD</emph> has been constructed having each of the angles at the base <emph>DB</emph> double of the remaining one. Q. E. F.</p>
     </div3>
     
