<div3 id="elem.12.1" n="1" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 1.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">Similar polygons inscribed in circles are to one another as the squares on the diameters.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FGH</hi> be circles, let <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> be similar polygons inscribed in them, and let <hi rend="ital">BM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GN</hi> be diameters of the circles; I say that, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">GN</hi>, so is the polygon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> to the polygon <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GL</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FN</hi> be joined. </p>
      <p>Now, since the polygon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is similar to the polygon <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi>, the angle <hi rend="ital">BAE</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">GFL</hi>, and, as <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">GF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">FL</hi>. [VI. Def. I] </p>
      <p>Thus <hi rend="ital">BAE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GFL</hi> are two triangles which have one angle equal to one angle, namely the angle <hi rend="ital">BAE</hi> to the angle <hi rend="ital">GFL</hi>, and the sides about the equal angles proportional; therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABE</hi> is equiangular with the triangle <hi rend="ital">FGL</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.6" targOrder="U">VI. 6</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">FLG</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the angle <hi rend="ital">AEB</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">AMB</hi>, for they stand on the same circumference; [<ref target="elem.3.27" targOrder="U">III. 27</ref>] and the angle <hi rend="ital">FLG</hi> to the angle <hi rend="ital">FNG</hi>; therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">AMB</hi> is also equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">FNG</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the right angle <hi rend="ital">BAM</hi> is also equal to the right angle <hi rend="ital">GFN</hi>; [<ref target="elem.3.31" targOrder="U">III. 31</ref>] therefore the remaining angle is equal to the remaining angle. [<ref target="elem.1.32" targOrder="U">I. 32</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABM</hi> is equiangular with the triangle <hi rend="ital">FGN</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, proportionally, as <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">GN</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.4" targOrder="U">VI. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the ratio of the square on <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> to the square on <hi rend="ital">GN</hi> is duplicate of the ratio of <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GN</hi>, and the ratio of the polygon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> to the polygon <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi> is duplicate of the ratio of <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>; [<ref target="elem.6.20" targOrder="U">VI. 20</ref>] therefore also, as the square on <hi rend="ital">BM</hi> is to the square on <hi rend="ital">GN</hi>, so is the polygon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> to the polygon <hi rend="ital">FGHKL</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
