<div3 id="elem.11.25" n="25" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 25.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If a parallelepipedal solid be cut by a plane which is parallel to the opposite planes</hi>, <hi rend="ital">then</hi>, <hi rend="ital">as the base is to the base</hi>, <hi rend="ital">so will the solid be to the solid.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the parallelepipedal solid <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> be cut by the plane <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> which is parallel to the opposite planes <hi rend="ital">RA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DH</hi>; I say that, as the base <hi rend="ital">AEFV</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">EHCF</hi>, so is the solid <hi rend="ital">ABFU</hi> to the solid <hi rend="ital">EGCD</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let <hi rend="ital">AH</hi> be produced in each direction, let any number of straight lines whatever, <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KL</hi>, be made equal to <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, and any number whatever, <hi rend="ital">HM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MN</hi>, equal to <hi rend="ital">EH</hi>; and let the parallelograms <hi rend="ital">LP</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KV</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HW</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MS</hi> and the solids <hi rend="ital">LQ</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KR</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MT</hi> be completed. </p>
      <p>Then, since the straight lines <hi rend="ital">LK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> are equal to one another, the parallelograms <hi rend="ital">LP</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KV</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AF</hi> are also equal to one another, <hi rend="ital">KO</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AG</hi> are equal to one another, and further <hi rend="ital">LX</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KQ</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AR</hi> are equal to one another, for they are opposite. [<ref target="elem.11.24" targOrder="U">XI. 24</ref>] </p>
      <p>For the same reason the parallelograms <hi rend="ital">EC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HW</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MS</hi> are also equal to one another, <hi rend="ital">HG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HI</hi>, <hi rend="ital">IN</hi> are equal to one another, and further <hi rend="ital">DH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MY</hi>, <hi rend="ital">NT</hi> are equal to one another. </p>
      <p>Therefore in the solids <hi rend="ital">LQ</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KR</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AU</hi> three planes are equal to three planes. </p>
      <p>But the three planes are equal to the three opposite; therefore the three solids <hi rend="ital">LQ</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KR</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AU</hi> are equal to one another. </p>
      <p>For the same reason the three solids <hi rend="ital">ED</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MT</hi> are also equal to one another. </p>
      <p>Therefore, whatever multiple the base <hi rend="ital">LF</hi> is of the base <hi rend="ital">AF</hi>, the same multiple also is the solid <hi rend="ital">LU</hi> of the solid <hi rend="ital">AU</hi>. </p>
      <p>For the same reason, whatever multiple the base <hi rend="ital">NF</hi> is of the base <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>, the same multiple also is the solid <hi rend="ital">NU</hi> of the solid <hi rend="ital">HU</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, if the base <hi rend="ital">LF</hi> is equal to the base <hi rend="ital">NF</hi>, the solid <hi rend="ital">LU</hi> is also equal to the solid <hi rend="ital">NU</hi>; if the base <hi rend="ital">LF</hi> exceeds the base <hi rend="ital">NF</hi>, the solid <hi rend="ital">LU</hi> also exceeds the solid <hi rend="ital">NU</hi>; and, if one falls short, the other falls short. </p>
      <p>Therefore, there being four magnitudes, the two bases <hi rend="ital">AF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>, and the two solids <hi rend="ital">AU</hi>, <hi rend="ital">UH</hi>, equimultiples have been taken of the base <hi rend="ital">AF</hi> and the solid <hi rend="ital">AU</hi>, namely the base <hi rend="ital">LF</hi> and the solid <hi rend="ital">LU</hi>, and equimultiples of the base <hi rend="ital">HF</hi> and the solid <hi rend="ital">HU</hi>, namely the base <hi rend="ital">NF</hi> and the solid <hi rend="ital">NU</hi>, and it has been proved that, if the base <hi rend="ital">LF</hi> exceeds the base <hi rend="ital">FN</hi>, the solid <hi rend="ital">LU</hi> also exceeds the solid <hi rend="ital">NU</hi>, if the bases are equal, the solids are equal, and if the base falls short, the solid falls short. </p>
      <p>Therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">AF</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>, so is the solid <hi rend="ital">AU</hi> to the solid <hi rend="ital">UH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.5" targOrder="U">V. Def. 5</ref>] Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
