<div3 id="elem.13.10" n="10" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 10.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If an equilateral pentagon be inscribed in a circle</hi>, <hi rend="ital">the square on the side of the pentagon is equal to the squares on the side of the hexagon and on that of the decagon inscribed in the same circle.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> be a circle, and let the equilateral pentagon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> be inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi>. </p>
      <p>I say that the square on the side of the pentagon <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi> is equal to the squares on the side of the hexagon and on that of the decagon inscribed in the circle <hi rend="ital">ABCDE</hi>. </p>
      <p>For let the centre of the circle, the point <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, be taken, let <hi rend="ital">AF</hi> be joined and carried through to the point <hi rend="ital">G</hi>, let <hi rend="ital">FB</hi> be joined, let <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> be drawn from <hi rend="ital">F</hi> perpendicular to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> and be carried through to <hi rend="ital">K</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KB</hi> be joined, let <hi rend="ital">FL</hi> be again drawn from <hi rend="ital">F</hi> perpendicular to <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>, and be carried through to <hi rend="ital">M</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">KN</hi> be joined. </p>
      <p>Since the circumference <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is equal to the circumference <hi rend="ital">AEDG</hi>, and in them <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">AED</hi>, therefore the remainder, the circumference <hi rend="ital">CG</hi>, is equal to the remainder <hi rend="ital">GD</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> belongs to a pentagon; therefore <hi rend="ital">CG</hi> belongs to a decagon. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">FA</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">FB</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> is perpendicular, therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">AFK</hi> is also equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KFB</hi>. [<ref target="elem.1.5" targOrder="U">I. 5</ref>, <ref target="elem.1.26" targOrder="U">I. 26</ref>] </p>
      <p>Hence the circumference <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is also equal to <hi rend="ital">KB</hi>; [<ref target="elem.3.26" targOrder="U">III. 26</ref>] therefore the circumference <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is double of the circumference <hi rend="ital">BK</hi>; therefore the straight line <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is a side of a decagon. </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is also double of <hi rend="ital">KM</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now, since the circumference <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is double of the circumference <hi rend="ital">BK</hi>, while the circumference <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is equal to the circumference <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, therefore the circumference <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is also double of the circumference <hi rend="ital">BK</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the circumference <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is also double of <hi rend="ital">CG</hi>; therefore the circumference <hi rend="ital">CG</hi> is equal to the circumference <hi rend="ital">BK</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">BK</hi> is double of <hi rend="ital">KM</hi>, since <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> is so also; therefore <hi rend="ital">CG</hi> is also double of <hi rend="ital">KM</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, further, the circumference <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> is also double of the circumference <hi rend="ital">BK</hi>, for the circumference <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the whole circumference <hi rend="ital">GB</hi> is also double of <hi rend="ital">BM</hi>; hence the angle <hi rend="ital">GFB</hi> is also double of the angle <hi rend="ital">BFM</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.33" targOrder="U">VI. 33</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the angle <hi rend="ital">GFB</hi> is also double of the angle <hi rend="ital">FAB</hi>, for the angle <hi rend="ital">FAB</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">ABF</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">BFN</hi> is also equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">FAB</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the angle <hi rend="ital">ABF</hi> is common to the two triangles <hi rend="ital">ABF</hi> and <hi rend="ital">BFN</hi>; therefore the remaining angle <hi rend="ital">AFB</hi> is equal to the remaining angle <hi rend="ital">BNF</hi>; [<ref target="elem.1.32" targOrder="U">I. 32</ref>] therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">ABF</hi> is equiangular with the triangle <hi rend="ital">BFN</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, proportionally, as the straight line <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">BF</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">FB</hi> to <hi rend="ital">BN</hi>; [<ref target="elem.6.4" targOrder="U">VI. 4</ref>] therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BN</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">BF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.17" targOrder="U">VI. 17</ref>] </p>
      <p>Again, since <hi rend="ital">AL</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">LK</hi>, while <hi rend="ital">LN</hi> is common and at right angles, therefore the base <hi rend="ital">KN</hi> is equal to the base <hi rend="ital">AN</hi>; [<ref target="elem.1.4" targOrder="U">I. 4</ref>] therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">LKN</hi> is also equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">LAN</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the angle <hi rend="ital">LAN</hi> is equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KBN</hi>; therefore the angle <hi rend="ital">LKN</hi> is also equal to the angle <hi rend="ital">KBN</hi>. </p>
      <p>And the angle at <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is common to the two triangles <hi rend="ital">AKB</hi> and <hi rend="ital">AKN</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore the remaining angle <hi rend="ital">AKB</hi> is equal to the remaining angle <hi rend="ital">KNA</hi>; [<ref target="elem.1.32" targOrder="U">I. 32</ref>] therefore the triangle <hi rend="ital">KBA</hi> is equiangular with the triangle <hi rend="ital">KNA</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, proportionally, as the straight line <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> to <hi rend="ital">AN</hi>; [<ref target="elem.6.4" targOrder="U">VI. 4</ref>] therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AN</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>. [<ref target="elem.6.17" targOrder="U">VI. 17</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BN</hi> was also proved equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">BF</hi>; <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BN</hi> together with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AN</hi>, that is, the square on <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> [<ref target="elem.2.2" targOrder="U">II. 2</ref>], is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">BF</hi> together with the square on <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>. </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">BA</hi> is a side of the pentagon, <hi rend="ital">BF</hi> of the hexagon [<ref target="elem.4.15.p.1" targOrder="U">IV. 15, Por.</ref>], and <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> of the decagon. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
