<div3 id="elem.5.3" n="3" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 3.</head>
      <p><emph>If a first magnitude be the same multiple of a second that a third is of a fourth</emph>, <emph>and if equimultiples be taken of the first and third</emph>, <emph>then also</emph> ex aequali <emph>the magnitudes taken will be equimultiples respectively</emph>, <emph>the one of the second and the other of the fourth</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let a first magnitude <emph>A</emph> be the same multiple of a second <emph>B</emph> that a third <emph>C</emph> is of a fourth <emph>D</emph>, and let equimultiples <emph>EF</emph>, <emph>GH</emph> be taken of <emph>A</emph>, <emph>C</emph>; I say that <emph>EF</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>B</emph> that <emph>GH</emph> is of <emph>D</emph>. </p>
      <p>For, since <emph>EF</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>A</emph> that <emph>GH</emph> is of <emph>C</emph>, therefore, as many magnitudes as there are in <emph>EF</emph> equal to <emph>A</emph>, so many also are there in <emph>GH</emph> equal to <emph>C</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>EF</emph> be divided into the magnitudes <emph>EK</emph>, <emph>KF</emph> equal to <emph>A</emph>, and <emph>GH</emph> into the magnitudes <emph>GL</emph>, <emph>LH</emph> equal to <emph>C</emph>; then the multitude of the magnitudes <emph>EK</emph>, <emph>KF</emph> will be equal to the multitude of the magnitudes <emph>GL</emph>, <emph>LH</emph>. </p>
      <p>And, since <emph>A</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>B</emph> that <emph>C</emph> is of <emph>D</emph>, while <emph>EK</emph> is equal to <emph>A</emph>, and <emph>GL</emph> to <emph>C</emph>, therefore <emph>EK</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>B</emph> that <emph>GL</emph> is of <emph>D</emph>. </p>
      <p>For the same reason </p>
      <p><emph>KF</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>B</emph> that <emph>LH</emph> is of <emph>D</emph>. </p>
      <p>Since, then, a first magnitude <emph>EK</emph> is the same multiple of a second <emph>B</emph> that a third <emph>GL</emph> is of a fourth <emph>D</emph>, and a fifth <emph>KF</emph> is also the same multiple of the second <emph>B</emph> that a sixth <emph>LH</emph> is of the fourth <emph>D</emph>, therefore the sum of the first and fifth, <emph>EF</emph>, is also the same multiple of the second <emph>B</emph> that the sum of the third and sixth, <emph>GH</emph>, is of the fourth <emph>D</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.2" targOrder="U">V. 2</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
