<div3 id="elem.5.16" n="16" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 16.</head>
      <p><emph>If four magnitudes be proportional</emph>, <emph>they will also be proportional alternately</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>A</emph>, <emph>B</emph>, <emph>C</emph>, <emph>D</emph> be four proportional magnitudes, so that, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, so is <emph>C</emph> to <emph>D</emph>; I say that they will also be so alternately, that is, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>C</emph>, so is <emph>B</emph> to <emph>D</emph>. </p>
      <p>For of <emph>A</emph>, <emph>B</emph> let equimultiples <emph>E</emph>, <emph>F</emph> be taken, and of <emph>C</emph>, <emph>D</emph> other, chance, equimultiples <emph>G</emph>, <emph>H</emph>. </p>
      <p>Then, since <emph>E</emph> is the same multiple of <emph>A</emph> that <emph>F</emph> is of <emph>B</emph>, and parts have the same ratio as the same multiples of them, [<ref target="elem.5.15" targOrder="U">V. 15</ref>] therefore, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, so is <emph>E</emph> to <emph>F</emph>. </p>
      <p>But as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, so is <emph>C</emph> to <emph>D</emph>; therefore also, as <emph>C</emph> is to <emph>D</emph>, so is <emph>E</emph> to <emph>F</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.11" targOrder="U">V. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>Again, since <emph>G</emph>, <emph>H</emph> are equimultiples of <emph>C</emph>, <emph>D</emph>, therefore, as <emph>C</emph> is to <emph>D</emph>, so is <emph>G</emph> to <emph>H</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.15" targOrder="U">V. 15</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, as <emph>C</emph> is to <emph>D</emph>, so is <emph>E</emph> to <emph>F</emph>; therefore also, as <emph>E</emph> is to <emph>F</emph>, so is <emph>G</emph> to <emph>H</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.11" targOrder="U">V. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, if four magnitudes be proportional, and the first be greater than the third, <hi rend="center">the second will also be greater than the fourth;</hi> if equal, equal; and if less, less. [<ref target="elem.5.14" targOrder="U">V. 14</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore, if <emph>E</emph> is in excess of <emph>G</emph>, <emph>F</emph> is also in excess of <emph>H</emph>, if equal, equal, and if less, less. </p>
      <p>Now <emph>E</emph>, <emph>F</emph> are equimultiples of <emph>A</emph>, <emph>B</emph>, and <emph>G</emph>, <emph>H</emph> other, chance, equimultiples of <emph>C</emph>, <emph>D</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>C</emph>, so is <emph>B</emph> to <emph>D</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.5" targOrder="U">V. Def. 5</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.
<note n="3" type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
        <p><quote><hi rend="bold">Let A, B, C, D be four proportional magnitudes, so that, as A is to B, so is C to D</hi>.</quote>
 In a number of expressions like this it is absolutely necessary, when translating into English, to interpolate words which are not in the Greek. Thus the Greek here is: <foreign lang="greek">Ἕστω τέσσαρα μεγέθη ἀνάλογον τὰ Α, Β, Γ, Δ, ὡς τὸ Α πρὸς τὸ Β, οὕτως τὸ Γ πρὸς τὸ Δ</foreign>, literally <quote>Let <emph>A</emph>, <emph>B</emph>, <emph>C</emph>, <emph>D</emph> be four proportional magnitudes, as <emph>A</emph> to <emph>B</emph>, so <emph>C</emph> to <emph>D</emph>.</quote>
 The same remark applies to the corresponding expressions in the next propositions, <ref target="elem.5.17 elem.5.18" targOrder="U">V. 17, 18</ref>, and to other forms of expression in <ref target="elem.5.20 elem.5.21 elem.5.22 elem.5.23" targOrder="U">V. 20-23</ref> and later propositions: e.g. in <ref target="elem.5.20" targOrder="U">V. 20</ref> we have a phrase meaning literally <quote>Let there be magnitudes...which taken two and two are in the same ratio, as <emph>A</emph> to <emph>B</emph>, so <emph>D</emph> to <emph>E</emph>,</quote>
 etc.: in <ref target="elem.5.21" targOrder="U">V. 21</ref> <quote>(magnitudes)...which taken two and two are in the same ratio, and let the proportion of them be perturbed, as <emph>A</emph> to <emph>B</emph>, so <emph>E</emph> to <emph>F</emph>,</quote>
 etc. In all such cases (where the Greek is so terse as to be almost ungrammatical) I shall insert the words necessary in English, without further remark.</p>
       </note></p>
     </div3>
     
