<div3 id="elem.10.56" n="56" type="propositions 48&#x2014;84">
      <head>PROPOSITION 56.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If an area be contained by a rational straight line and the third binomial, the <quote>side</quote>
 of the area is the irrational straight line called a second bimedial.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the area <hi rend="ital">ABCD</hi> be contained by the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> and the third binomial <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> divided into its terms at <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, of which terms <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is the greater; I say that the <quote>side</quote>
 of the area <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is the irrational straight line called a second bimedial. </p>
      <p>For let the same construction be made as before. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">AD</hi> is a third binomial straight line, therefore <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">ED</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only, the square on <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">ED</hi> by the square on a straight line commensurable with <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, and neither of the terms <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">ED</hi> is commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.def.2.3" targOrder="U">X. Deff. II. 3</ref>] </p>
      <p>Then, in manner similar to the foregoing, we shall prove that <hi rend="ital">MO</hi> is the <quote>side</quote>
 of the area <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">MN</hi>, <hi rend="ital">NO</hi> are medial straight lines commensurable in square only; so that <hi rend="ital">MO</hi> is bimedial. </p>
      <p>It is next to be proved that it is also a second bimedial straight line. </p>
      <p>Since <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, that is, with <hi rend="ital">EK</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is commensurable with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EK</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.13" targOrder="U">X. 13</ref>] </p>
      <p>And they are rational; <hi rend="ital">FE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EK</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EL</hi>, that is, <hi rend="ital">MR</hi>, is medial. [<ref target="elem.10.21" targOrder="U">X. 21</ref>] </p>
      <p>And it is contained by <hi rend="ital">MN</hi>, <hi rend="ital">NO</hi>; therefore the rectangle <hi rend="ital">MN</hi>, <hi rend="ital">NO</hi> is medial. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">MO</hi> is a second bimedial straight line. [<ref target="elem.10.38" targOrder="U">X. 38</ref>] Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
