<div3 id="elem.2.9" n="9" type="proposition">
      <head>Proposition 9.</head>
      <p><emph>If a straight line be cut into equal and unequal segments</emph>, <emph>the squares on the unequal segments of the whole are double of the square on the half and of the square on the straight line between the points of section</emph>.</p>
      <p>For let a straight line <emph>AB</emph> be cut into equal segments at <emph>C</emph>, and into unequal segments at <emph>D</emph>;</p>
      <p>I say that the squares on <emph>AD</emph>, <emph>DB</emph> are double of the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CD</emph>. </p>
      <p>For let <emph>CE</emph> be drawn from <emph>C</emph> at right angles to <emph>AB</emph>, and let it be made equal to either <emph>AC</emph> or <emph>CB</emph>; let <emph>EA</emph>, <emph>EB</emph> be joined, let <emph>DF</emph> be drawn through <emph>D</emph> parallel to <emph>EC</emph>, and <emph>FG</emph> through <emph>F</emph> parallel to <emph>AB</emph>, and let <emph>AF</emph> be joined.</p>
      <p>Then, since <emph>AC</emph> is equal to <emph>CE</emph>, <hi rend="center">the angle <emph>EAC</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>AEC</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>And, since the angle at <emph>C</emph> is right, <hi rend="center">the remaining angles <emph>EAC</emph>, <emph>AEC</emph> are equal to one right angle. [<ref target="elem.1.32" targOrder="U">I. 32</ref>]</hi></p>
      <p>And they are equal; <hi rend="center">therefore each of the angles <emph>CEA</emph>, <emph>CAE</emph> is half a right angle.</hi></p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="center">each of the angles <emph>CEB</emph>, <emph>EBC</emph> is also half a right angle; therefore the whole angle <emph>AEB</emph> is right.</hi></p>
      <p>And, since the angle <emph>GEF</emph> is half a right angle, <emph>EGF</emph> is right, for it is equal to the interior and opposite angle <emph>ECB</emph>, [<ref target="elem.1.29" targOrder="U">I. 29</ref>] <hi rend="center">the remaining angle <emph>EFG</emph> is half a right angle; [<ref target="elem.1.32" targOrder="U">I. 32</ref>] therefore the angle <emph>GEF</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>EFG</emph>, so that the side <emph>EG</emph> is also equal to <emph>GF</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.6" targOrder="U">I. 6</ref>]</hi></p>
      <p>Again, since the angle at <emph>B</emph> is half a right angle, and the angle <emph>FDB</emph> is right, for it is again equal to the interior and opposite angle <emph>ECB</emph>, [<ref target="elem.1.29" targOrder="U">I. 29</ref>] <hi rend="center">the remaining angle <emph>BFD</emph> is half a right angle; [<ref target="elem.1.32" targOrder="U">I. 32</ref>] therefore the angle at <emph>B</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>DFB</emph>, so that the side <emph>FD</emph> is also equal to the side <emph>DB</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.6" targOrder="U">I. 6</ref>]</hi></p>
      <p>Now, since <emph>AC</emph> is equal to <emph>CE</emph>, <hi rend="center">the square on <emph>AC</emph> is also equal to the square on <emph>CE</emph>; therefore the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CE</emph> are double of the square on <emph>AC</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>But the square on <emph>EA</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CE</emph>, for the angle <emph>ACE</emph> is right; [<ref target="elem.1.47" targOrder="U">I. 47</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore the square on <emph>EA</emph> is double of the square on <emph>AC</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>Again, since <emph>EG</emph> is equal to <emph>GF</emph>, <hi rend="center">the square on <emph>EG</emph> is also equal to the square on <emph>GF</emph>; therefore the squares on <emph>EG</emph>, <emph>GF</emph> are double of the square on <emph>GF</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>But the square on <emph>EF</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>EG</emph>, <emph>GF</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the square on <emph>EF</emph> is double of the square on <emph>GF</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>But <emph>GF</emph> is equal to <emph>CD</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.34" targOrder="U">I. 34</ref>] therefore the square on <emph>EF</emph> is double of the square on <emph>CD</emph>.</p>
      <p>But the square on <emph>EA</emph> is also double of the square on <emph>AC</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the squares on <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EF</emph> are double of the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CD</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>And the square on <emph>AF</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>EF</emph>, for the angle <emph>AEF</emph> is right; [<ref target="elem.1.47" targOrder="U">I. 47</ref>] therefore the square on <emph>AF</emph> is double of the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CD</emph>.</p>
      <p>But the squares on <emph>AD</emph>, <emph>DF</emph> are equal to the square on <emph>AF</emph>, for the angle at <emph>D</emph> is right; [<ref target="elem.1.47" targOrder="U">I. 47</ref>] therefore the squares on <emph>AD</emph>, <emph>DF</emph> are double of the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CD</emph>. </p>
      <p>And <emph>DF</emph> is equal to <emph>DB</emph>; therefore the squares on <emph>AD</emph>, <emph>DB</emph> are double of the squares on <emph>AC</emph>, <emph>CD</emph>.</p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
