<div3 id="elem.9.3" n="3" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 3.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If a cube number by multiplying itself make some number, the product will be cube.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the cube number <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying itself make <hi rend="ital">B</hi>; I say that <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is cube. </p>
      <p>For let <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, the side of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, be taken, and let <hi rend="ital">C</hi> by multiplying itself make <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>It is then manifest that <hi rend="ital">C</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">D</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">C</hi> by multiplying itself has made <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">C</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">D</hi> according to the units in itself. </p>
      <p>But further the unit also measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi> according to the units in it; therefore, as the unit is to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">C</hi> to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.def.20" targOrder="U">VII. Def. 20</ref>] </p>
      <p>Again, since <hi rend="ital">C</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">D</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">D</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">A</hi> according to the units in <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>But the unit also measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi> according to the units in it; therefore, as the unit is to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">D</hi> to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as the unit is to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">C</hi> to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; therefore also, as the unit is to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">C</hi> to <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">D</hi> to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore between the unit and the number <hi rend="ital">A</hi> two mean proportional numbers <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> have fallen in continued proportion. </p>
      <p>Again, since <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying itself has made <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">B</hi> according to the units in itself. </p>
      <p>But the unit also measures <hi rend="ital">A</hi> according to the units in it; therefore, as the unit is to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">A</hi> to <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.def.20" targOrder="U">VII. Def. 20</ref>] </p>
      <p>But between the unit and <hi rend="ital">A</hi> two mean proportional numbers have fallen; therefore two mean proportional numbers will also fall between <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. [<ref target="elem.8.8" targOrder="U">VIII. 8</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, if two mean proportional numbers fall between two numbers, and the first be cube, the second will also be cube. [<ref target="elem.8.23" targOrder="U">VIII. 23</ref>] </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">A</hi> is cube; therefore <hi rend="ital">B</hi> is also cube. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
