<div3 id="elem.11.37" n="37" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 37.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">If four straight lines be proportional</hi>, <hi rend="ital">the parallelepipedal solids on them which are similar and similarly described will also be proportional; and</hi>, <hi rend="ital">if the parallelepipedal solids on them which are similar and similarly described be proportional</hi>, <hi rend="ital">the straight lines will themselves also be proportional.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> be four straight lines in proportion, so that, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>; and let there be described on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> the similar and similarly situated parallelepipedal solids <hi rend="ital">KA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">LC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">ME</hi>, <hi rend="ital">NG</hi>; I say that, as <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">LC</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> to <hi rend="ital">NG</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, since the parallelepipedal solid <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> is similar to <hi rend="ital">LC</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">LC</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. [<ref target="elem.11.33" targOrder="U">XI. 33</ref>] </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> also has to <hi rend="ital">NG</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. [<hi rend="ital">id</hi>.] </p>
      <p>And, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore also, as <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">LC</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> to <hi rend="ital">NG</hi>. </p>
      <p>Next, as the solid <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is to the solid <hi rend="ital">LC</hi>, so let the solid <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> be to the solid <hi rend="ital">NG</hi>; I say that, as the straight line <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. </p>
      <p>For since, again, <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">LC</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, [<ref target="elem.11.33" targOrder="U">XI. 33</ref>] and <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> also has to <hi rend="ital">NG</hi> the ratio triplicate of that which <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> has to <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, [<hi rend="ital">id</hi>.] and, as <hi rend="ital">KA</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">LC</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">ME</hi> to <hi rend="ital">NG</hi>, therefore also, as <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> to <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
