<div3 id="elem.10.1" n="1" type="propositions i&#x2014;47">
      <head>PROPOSITION 1.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">Two unequal magnitudes being set out, if from the greater there be subtracted a magnitude greater than its half, and from that which is left a magnitude greater than its half, and if this process be repeated continually, there will be left some magnitude which will be less than the lesser magnitude set out</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB, C</hi> be two unequal magnitudes of which <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is the greater: I say that, if from <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> there be subtracted a magnitude greater than its half, and from that which is left a magnitude greater than its half, and if this process be repeated continually, there will be left some magnitude which will be less than the magnitude <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>For <hi rend="ital">C</hi> if multiplied will sometime be greater than <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>. [cf. <ref target="elem.5.def.4" targOrder="U">v. Def. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>Let it be multiplied, and let <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> be a multiple of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, and greater than. <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>; let <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> be divided into the parts <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GE</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, from <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> let there be subtracted <hi rend="ital">BH</hi> greater than its half, and, from <hi rend="ital">AH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> greater than its half, and let this process be repeated continually until the divisions in <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> are equal in multitude with the divisions in <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let, then, <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HB</hi> be divisions which are equal in multitude with <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GE</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is greater than <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, and from <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> there has been subtracted <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> less than its half, and, from <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">BH</hi> greater than its half, therefore the remainder <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> is greater than the remainder <hi rend="ital">HA</hi>. </p>
      <p>And, since <hi rend="ital">GD</hi> is greater than <hi rend="ital">HA</hi>, and there has been subtracted, from <hi rend="ital">GD</hi>, the half <hi rend="ital">GF</hi>, and, from <hi rend="ital">HA</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HK</hi> greater than its half, therefore the remainder <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> is greater than the remainder <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">C</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">C</hi> is also greater than <hi rend="ital">AK</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> is less than <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore there is left of the magnitude <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> the magnitude <hi rend="ital">AK</hi> which is less than the lesser magnitude set out, namely <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. Q. E. D. </p>
      <p>And the theorem can be similarly proved even if the parts subtracted be halves.</p>
     </div3>
     
