<div3 id="elem.6.33" n="33" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 33.</head>
      <p><emph>In equal circles angles have the same ratio as the circumferences on which they stand</emph>, <emph>whether they stand at the centres or at the circumferences</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>ABC</emph>, <emph>DEF</emph> be equal circles, and let the angles <emph>BGC</emph>, <emph>EHF</emph> be angles at their centres <emph>G</emph>, <emph>H</emph>, and the angles <emph>BAC</emph>, <emph>EDF</emph> angles at the circumferences; I say that, as the circumference <emph>BC</emph> is to the circumference <emph>EF</emph>, so is the angle <emph>BGC</emph> to the angle <emph>EHF</emph>, and the angle <emph>BAC</emph> to the angle <emph>EDF</emph>. </p>
      <p>For let any number of consecutive circumferences <emph>CK</emph>, <emph>KL</emph> be made equal to the circumference <emph>BC</emph>, and any number of consecutive circumferences <emph>FM</emph>, <emph>MN</emph> equal to the circumference <emph>EF</emph>; and let <emph>GK</emph>, <emph>GL</emph>, <emph>HM</emph>, <emph>HN</emph> be joined. </p>
      <p>Then, since the circumferences <emph>BC</emph>, <emph>CK</emph>, <emph>KL</emph> are equal to one another, the angles <emph>BGC</emph>, <emph>CGK</emph>, <emph>KGL</emph> are also equal to one another; [<ref target="elem.3.27" targOrder="U">III. 27</ref>] <emph>BL</emph> is of <emph>BC</emph>, that multiple also is the angle <emph>BGL</emph> of the angle <emph>BGC</emph>. </p>
      <p>For the same reason also, whatever multiple the circumference <emph>NE</emph> is of <emph>EF</emph>, that multiple also is the angle <emph>NHE</emph> of the angle <emph>EHF</emph>. </p>
      <p>If then the circumference <emph>BL</emph> is equal to the circumference <emph>EN</emph>, the angle <emph>BGL</emph> is also equal to the angle <emph>EHN</emph>; [<ref target="elem.3.27" targOrder="U">III. 27</ref>] if the circumference <emph>BL</emph> is greater than the circumference <emph>EN</emph>, the angle <emph>BGL</emph> is also greater than the angle <emph>EHN</emph>; and, if less, less. </p>
      <p>There being then four magnitudes, two circumferences <emph>BC</emph>, <emph>EF</emph>, and two angles <emph>BGC</emph>, <emph>EHF</emph>, there have been taken, of the circumference <emph>BC</emph> and the angle <emph>BGC</emph> equimultiples, namely the circumference <emph>BL</emph> and the angle <emph>BGL</emph>, and of the circumference <emph>EF</emph> and the angle <emph>EHF</emph> equimultiples, namely the circumference <emph>EN</emph> and the angle <emph>EHN</emph>. </p>
      <p>And it has been proved that, if the circumference <emph>BL</emph> is in excess of the circumference <emph>EN</emph>, the angle <emph>BGL</emph> is also in excess of the angle <emph>EHN</emph>; if equal, equal; and if less, less. </p>
      <p>Therefore, as the circumference <emph>BC</emph> is to <emph>EF</emph>, so is the angle <emph>BGC</emph> to the angle <emph>EHF</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.5" targOrder="U">V. Def. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, as the angle <emph>BGC</emph> is to the angle <emph>EHF</emph>, so is the angle <emph>BAC</emph> to the angle <emph>EDF</emph>; for they are doubles respectively. </p>
      <p>Therefore also, as the circumference <emph>BC</emph> is to the circumference <emph>EF</emph>, so is the angle <emph>BGC</emph> to the angle <emph>EHF</emph>, and the angle <emph>BAC</emph> to the angle <emph>EDF</emph>. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
    
