<div3 id="elem.12.5" n="5" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 5.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">Pyramids which are of the same height and have triangular bases are to one another as the bases.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let there be pyramids of the same height, of which the triangles <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> are the bases and the points <hi rend="ital">G</hi>, <hi rend="ital">H</hi> the vertices; I say that, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, if the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is not to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, then, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so will the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> be either to some solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> or to a greater. </p>
      <p>Let it, first, be in that ratio to a less solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi>, and let the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> be divided into two pyramids equal to one another and similar to the whole and into two equal prisms; then the two prisms are greater than the half of the whole pyramid. [<ref target="elem.12.3" targOrder="U">XII. 3</ref>] </p>
      <p>Again, let the pyramids arising from the division be similarly divided, and let this be done continually until there are left over from the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> some pyramids which are less than the excess by which the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> exceeds the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi>. [X. I] </p>
      <p>Let such be left, and let them be, for the sake of argument, <hi rend="ital">DQRS</hi>, <hi rend="ital">STUH</hi>; therefore the remainders, the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>, are greater than the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> also be divided similarly, and a similar number of times, with the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>; therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so are the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.12.4" targOrder="U">XII. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so also is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi>; therefore also, as the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is to the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi>, so are the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>; [V. II] therefore, alternately, as the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is to the prisms in it, so is the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> to the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.5.16" targOrder="U">V. 16</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is greater than the prisms in it; therefore the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> is also greater than the prisms in the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it is also less: which is impossible. </p>
      <p>Therefore the prism <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is not to any solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>. </p>
      <p>Similarly it can be proved that neither is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to any solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>. </p>
      <p>I say next that neither is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to any solid greater than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, if possible, let it be in that ratio to a greater solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi>; therefore, inversely, as the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, so is the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, as the solid <hi rend="ital">W</hi> is to the solid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to some solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi>, as was before proved; [<ref target="elem.12.2.l.1" targOrder="U">XII. 2, Lemma</ref>] therefore also, as the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> to some solid less than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi>: [V. II] which was proved absurd. </p>
      <p>Therefore the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> is not to any solid greater than the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi> as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it was proved that neither is it in that ratio to a less solid. </p>
      <p>Therefore, as the base <hi rend="ital">ABC</hi> is to the base <hi rend="ital">DEF</hi>, so is the pyramid <hi rend="ital">ABCG</hi> to the pyramid <hi rend="ital">DEFH</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
