<div3 id="elem.2.11" n="11" type="proposition">
      <head>Proposition 11.</head>
      <p><emph>To cut a given straight line so that the rectangle contained by the whole and one of the segments is equal to the square on the remaining segment</emph>.</p>
      <p>Let <emph>AB</emph> be the given straight line; thus it is required to cut <emph>AB</emph> so that the rectangle contained by the whole and one of the segments is equal to the square on the remaining segment.</p>
      <p>For let the square <emph>ABDC</emph> be described on <emph>AB</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.46" targOrder="U">I. 46</ref>] let <emph>AC</emph> be bisected at the point <emph>E</emph>, and let <emph>BE</emph> be joined; let <emph>CA</emph> be drawn through to <emph>F</emph>, and let <emph>EF</emph> be made equal to <emph>BE</emph>; let the square <emph>FH</emph> be described on <emph>AF</emph>, and let <emph>GH</emph> be drawn through to <emph>K</emph>. </p>
      <p>I say that <emph>AB</emph> has been cut at <emph>H</emph> so as to make the rectangle contained by <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BH</emph> equal to the square on <emph>AH</emph>.</p>
      <p>For, since the straight line <emph>AC</emph> has been bisected at <emph>E</emph>, and <emph>FA</emph> is added to it, <hi rend="center">the rectangle contained by <emph>CF</emph>, <emph>FA</emph> together with the square on <emph>AE</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>EF</emph>. [<ref target="elem.2.6" targOrder="U">II. 6</ref>]</hi></p>
      <p>But <emph>EF</emph> is equal to <emph>EB</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the rectangle <emph>CF</emph>, <emph>FA</emph> together with the square on <emph>AE</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>EB</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>But the squares on <emph>BA</emph>, <emph>AE</emph> are equal to the square on <emph>EB</emph>, for the angle at <emph>A</emph> is right; [<ref target="elem.1.47" targOrder="U">I. 47</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore the rectangle <emph>CF</emph>, <emph>FA</emph> together with the square on <emph>AE</emph> is equal to the squares on <emph>BA</emph>, <emph>AE</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>Let the square on <emph>AE</emph> be subtracted from each; <hi rend="center">therefore the rectangle <emph>CF</emph>, <emph>FA</emph> which remains is equal to the square on <emph>AB</emph>.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>Now the rectangle <emph>CF</emph>, <emph>FA</emph> is <emph>FK</emph>, for <emph>AF</emph> is equal to <emph>FG</emph>; and the square on <emph>AB</emph> is <emph>AD</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>FK</emph> is equal to <emph>AD</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>Let <emph>AK</emph> be subtracted from each; <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>FH</emph> which remains is equal to <emph>HD</emph>.</hi></p>
      <p>And <emph>HD</emph> is the rectangle <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BH</emph>, for <emph>AB</emph> is equal to <emph>BD</emph>; and <emph>FH</emph> is the square on <emph>AH</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the rectangle contained by <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BH</emph> is equal to the square on <emph>HA</emph>. therefore the given straight line <emph>AB</emph> has been cut at <emph>H</emph> so as to make the rectangle contained by <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BH</emph> equal to the square on <emph>HA</emph>. Q. E. F.</hi></p>
     </div3>
     
