<div3 id="elem.3.9" n="9" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 9.</head>
      <p><emph>If a point be taken within a circle</emph>, <emph>and more than two equal straight lines fall from the point on the circle</emph>, <emph>the point taken is the centre of the circle</emph>. </p>
      <p>Let <emph>ABC</emph> be a circle and <emph>D</emph> a point within it, and from <emph>D</emph> let more than two equal straight lines, namely <emph>DA</emph>, <emph>DB</emph>, <emph>DC</emph>, fall on the circle <emph>ABC</emph>; I say that the point <emph>D</emph> is the centre of the circle <emph>ABC</emph>. </p>
      <p>For let <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>BC</emph> be joined and bisected at the points <emph>E</emph>, <emph>F</emph>, and let <emph>ED</emph>, <emph>FD</emph> be joined and drawn through to the points <emph>G</emph>, <emph>K</emph>, <emph>H</emph>, <emph>L</emph>. </p>
      <p>Then, since <emph>AE</emph> is equal to <emph>EB</emph>, and <emph>ED</emph> is common, <hi rend="center">the two sides <emph>AE</emph>, <emph>ED</emph> are equal to the two sides <emph>BE</emph>, <emph>ED</emph>;</hi> and the base <emph>DA</emph> is equal to the base <emph>DB</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the angle <emph>AED</emph> is equal to the angle <emph>BED</emph>. [<ref target="elem.1.8" targOrder="U">I. 8</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore each of the angles <emph>AED</emph>, <emph>BED</emph> is right; [<ref target="elem.1.def.10" targOrder="U">I. Def. 10</ref>] therefore <emph>GK</emph> cuts <emph>AB</emph> into two equal parts and at right angles. </p>
      <p>And since, if in a circle a straight line cut a straight line into two equal parts and at right angles, the centre of the circle is on the cutting straight line, [<ref target="elem.3.1.p.1" targOrder="U">III. 1, Por.</ref>] <hi rend="center">the centre of the circle is on <emph>GK</emph>.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>For the same reason <hi rend="center">the centre of the circle <emph>ABC</emph> is also on <emph>HL</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>And the straight lines <emph>GK</emph>, <emph>HL</emph> have no other point common but the point <emph>D</emph>; <hi rend="center">therefore the point <emph>D</emph> is the centre of the circle <emph>ABC</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
