<div3 id="elem.7.24" n="24" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 24.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If two numbers be prime to any number, their product also will be prime to the same.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the two numbers <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi> be prime to any number <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, and let <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">B</hi> make <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; I say that <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> are prime to one another. </p>
      <p>For, if <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> are not prime to one another, some number will measure <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let a number measure them, and let it be <hi rend="ital">E</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">A</hi> are prime to one another, and a certain number <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> are prime to one another. [<ref target="elem.7.23" targOrder="U">VII. 23</ref>] </p>
      <p>As many times, then, as <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">D</hi>, so many units let there be in <hi rend="ital">F</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">F</hi> also measures <hi rend="ital">D</hi> according to the units in <hi rend="ital">E</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.16" targOrder="U">VII. 16</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">F</hi> has made <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.def.15" targOrder="U">VII. Def. 15</ref>] </p>
      <p>But, further, <hi rend="ital">A</hi> by multiplying <hi rend="ital">B</hi> has also made <hi rend="ital">D</hi>; therefore the product of <hi rend="ital">E</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi> is equal to the product of <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, if the product of the extremes be equal to that of the means, the four numbers are proportional; [<ref target="elem.7.19" targOrder="U">VII. 19</ref>] therefore, as <hi rend="ital">E</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, so is <hi rend="ital">B</hi> to <hi rend="ital">F</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">A</hi>, <hi rend="ital">E</hi> are prime to one another, numbers which are prime to one another are also the least of those which have the same ratio, [<ref target="elem.7.21" targOrder="U">VII. 21</ref>] and the least numbers of those which have the same ratio with them measure those which have the same ratio the same <ref target="elem.7.20" targOrder="U">VII. 20</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">B</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it also measures <hi rend="ital">C</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">E</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">B</hi>, <hi rend="ital">C</hi> which are prime to one another: which is impossible. [<ref target="elem.7.def.12" targOrder="U">VII. Def. 12</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore no number will measure the numbers <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">D</hi> are prime to one another. Q. E. D.
<note n="1. their product." type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes"><foreign lang="greek">ὁ ἐξ αὐτῶν γενόμενος</foreign>, literally <quote>the (number) produced from them,</quote>
 will henceforth be translated as <quote>their product.</quote>
</note></p>
     </div3>
     
