<div3 id="elem.1.42" n="42" type="proposition">
      <head>Proposition 42.</head>
      <div4 type="Enunc">
       <p>To construct, in a given rectilineal angle, a parallelogram equal to a given triangle.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 type="Proof">
       <p>Let <emph>ABC</emph> be the given triangle, and <emph>D</emph> the given rectilineal angle; thus it is required to construct in the rectilineal angle <emph>D</emph> a parallelogram equal to the triangle <emph>ABC</emph>. </p>
       <p>Let <emph>BC</emph> be bisected at <emph>E</emph>, and let <emph>AE</emph> be joined; on the straight line <emph>EC</emph>, and at the point <emph>E</emph> on it, let the angle <emph>CEF</emph> be constructed equal to the angle <emph>D</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.23" targOrder="U">I. 23</ref>] through <emph>A</emph> let <emph>AG</emph> be drawn parallel to <emph>EC</emph>, and [<ref target="elem.1.31" targOrder="U">I. 31</ref>] through <emph>C</emph> let <emph>CG</emph> be drawn parallel to <emph>EF</emph>.</p>
       <p>Then <emph>FECG</emph> is a parallelogram.</p>
       <p>And, since <emph>BE</emph> is equal to <emph>EC</emph>, <hi rend="center">the triangle <emph>ABE</emph> is also equal to the triangle <emph>AEC</emph>, for they are on equal bases <emph>BE</emph>, <emph>EC</emph> and in the same parallels <emph>BC</emph>, <emph>AG</emph>; [<ref target="elem.1.38" targOrder="U">I. 38</ref>] therefore the triangle <emph>ABC</emph> is double of the triangle <emph>AEC</emph>.</hi>
        </p>
       <p>But the parallelogram <emph>FECG</emph> is also double of the triangle <emph>AEC</emph>, for it has the same base with it and is in the same parallels with it; [<ref target="elem.1.41" targOrder="U">I. 41</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore the parallelogram <emph>FECG</emph> is equal to the triangle <emph>ABC</emph>.</hi></p>
       <p>And it has the angle <emph>CEF</emph> equal to the given angle <emph>D</emph>.</p>
       <p>Therefore the parallelogram <emph>FECG</emph> has been constructed equal to the given triangle <emph>ABC</emph>, in the angle <emph>CEF</emph> which is equal to <emph>D</emph>. Q. E. F.</p>
      </div4>
     </div3>
     
