<div3 id="elem.10.26" n="26" type="propositions i&#x2014;47">
      <head>PROPOSITION 26.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">4 medial area does not exceed a medial area by a rational area</hi>. </p>
      <p>For, if possible, let the medial area <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> exceed the medial area <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> by the rational area <hi rend="ital">DB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> be set out; to <hi rend="ital">EF</hi> let there be applied the rectangular parallelogram <hi rend="ital">FH</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, producing <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> as breadth, and let the rectangle <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> equal to <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> be subtracted; therefore the remainder <hi rend="ital">BD</hi> is equal to the remainder <hi rend="ital">KH</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">DB</hi> is rational; therefore <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> is also rational. </p>
      <p>Since, then, each of the rectangles <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is medial, and <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is equal to <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> to <hi rend="ital">FG</hi>, therefore each of the rectangles <hi rend="ital">FH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">FG</hi> is also medial. </p>
      <p>And they are applied to the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>; therefore each of the straight lines <hi rend="ital">HE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is rational and incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.22" targOrder="U">X. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>And, since [<hi rend="ital">DB</hi> is rational and is equal to <hi rend="ital">KH</hi>, therefore] <hi rend="ital">KH</hi> is [also] rational; and it is applied to the rational straight line <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>; <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> is rational and commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.20" targOrder="U">X. 20</ref>] </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is also rational, and is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">EF</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.13" targOrder="U">X. 13</ref>] </p>
      <p>And, as <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is to <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, so is the square on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> to the rectangle <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi> is incommensurable with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.11" targOrder="U">X. 11</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the squares on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> are commensurable with the square on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, for both are rational; and twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> is commensurable with the rectangle <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, for it is double of it; [<ref target="elem.10.6" targOrder="U">X. 6</ref>] therefore the squares on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> are incommensurable with twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>; [<ref target="elem.10.13" targOrder="U">X. 13</ref>] therefore also the sum of the squares on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> and twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>, that is, the square on <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> [<ref target="elem.2.4" targOrder="U">II. 4</ref>], is incommensurable with the squares on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.16" targOrder="U">X. 16</ref>] </p>
      <p>But the squares on <hi rend="ital">EG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GH</hi> are rational; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> is irrational. [<ref target="elem.10.def.4" targOrder="U">X. Def. 4</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">EH</hi> is irrational. </p>
      <p>But it is also rational: which is impossible. </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
