<div3 id="elem.7.2" n="2" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 2.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">Given two numbers not prime to one another, to find their greatest common measure.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> be the two given numbers not prime to one another. </p>
      <p>Thus it is required to find the greatest common measure of <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>If now <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>—and it also measures itself—<hi rend="ital">CD</hi> is a common measure of <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>. </p>
      <p>And it is manifest that it is also the greatest; for no greater number than <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> will measure <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>But, if <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> does not measure <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, then, the less of the numbers <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> being continually subtracted from the greater, some number will be left which will measure the one before it. </p>
      <p>For an unit will not be left; otherwise <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> will be prime to one another [<ref target="elem.7.1" targOrder="U">VII. 1</ref>], which is contrary to the hypothesis. </p>
      <p>Therefore some number will be left which will measure the one before it. </p>
      <p>Now let <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, measuring <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>, leave <hi rend="ital">EA</hi> less than itself, let <hi rend="ital">EA</hi>, measuring <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, leave <hi rend="ital">FC</hi> less than itself, and let <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> measure <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>. </p>
      <p>Since then, <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> will also measure <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it also measures itself; therefore it will also measure the whole <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> also measures <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it also measures <hi rend="ital">EA</hi>; therefore it will also measure the whole <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it also measures <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> is a common measure of <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>I say next that it is also the greatest. </p>
      <p>For, if <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> is not the greatest common measure of <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, some number which is greater than <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> will measure the numbers <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let such a number measure them, and let it be <hi rend="ital">G</hi>. </p>
      <p>Now, since <hi rend="ital">G</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>, while <hi rend="ital">CD</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>, <hi rend="ital">G</hi> also measures <hi rend="ital">BE</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it also measures the whole <hi rend="ital">BA</hi>; therefore it will also measure the remainder <hi rend="ital">AE</hi>. </p>
      <p>But <hi rend="ital">AE</hi> measures <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>; therefore <hi rend="ital">G</hi> will also measure <hi rend="ital">DF</hi>. </p>
      <p>But it also measures the whole <hi rend="ital">DC</hi>; therefore it will also measure the remainder <hi rend="ital">CF</hi>, that is, the greater will measure the less: which is impossible. </p>
      <p>Therefore no number which is greater than <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> will measure the numbers <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>; <hi rend="center">therefore <hi rend="ital">CF</hi> is the greatest common measure of <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CD</hi>.</hi>
      </p>
      <div4 id="elem.7.2.p.1" type="porism">
       <head>PORISM.</head>
       <p>From this it is manifest that, if a number measure two numbers, it will also measure their greatest common measure.</p>
      </div4>
      <trailer>Q. E. D.</trailer>
     </div3>
     
