<div3 id="elem.7.6" n="6" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 6.</head>
      <p>
       <hi rend="ital">If a number be parts of a number, and another be the same parts of another, the sum will also be the same parts of the sum that the one is of the one.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For let the number <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be parts of the number <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, and another, <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>, the same parts of another, <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, that <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>; I say that the sum of <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is also the same parts of the sum of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi> that <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>. </p>
      <p>For since, whatever parts <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> is also the same parts of <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, therefore, as many parts of <hi rend="ital">C</hi> as there are in <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, so many parts of <hi rend="ital">F</hi> are there also in <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be divided into the parts of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, namely <hi rend="ital">AG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GB</hi>, and <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> into the parts of <hi rend="ital">F</hi>, namely <hi rend="ital">DH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HE</hi>; thus the multitude of <hi rend="ital">AG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">GB</hi> will be equal to the multitude of <hi rend="ital">DH</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HE</hi>. </p>
      <p>And since, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AG</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, the same part is <hi rend="ital">DH</hi> of <hi rend="ital">F</hi> also, therefore, whatever part <hi rend="ital">AG</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, the same part also is the sum of <hi rend="ital">AG</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DH</hi> of the sum of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi>. [<ref target="elem.7.5" targOrder="U">VII. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>For the same reason, whatever part <hi rend="ital">GB</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, the same part also is the sum of <hi rend="ital">GB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">HE</hi> of the sum of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore, whatever parts <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, the same parts also is the sum of <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> of the sum of <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, <hi rend="ital">F</hi>. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
