<div3 id="elem.1.27" n="27" type="proposition">
      <head>Proposition 27.</head>
      <div4 type="Enunc">
       <p>If a straight line falling on two straight lines make the alternate angles equal to one another, the straight lines will be parallel to one another.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 type="Proof">
       <p>For let the straight line <emph>EF</emph> falling on the two straight <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>CD</emph> make the alternate angles <emph>AEF</emph>, <emph>EFD</emph> equal to one another;</p>
       <p>I say that <emph>AB</emph> is parallel to <emph>CD</emph>.</p>
       <p>For, if not, <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>CD</emph> when produced will meet either in the direction <emph>B</emph>, <emph>D</emph> or towards <emph>A</emph>, <emph>C</emph>. </p>
       <p>Let them be produced and meet, in the direction of <emph>B</emph>, <emph>D</emph>, at <emph>G</emph>.</p>
       <p>Then, in the triangle <emph>GEF</emph>, the exterior angle <emph>AEF</emph> is equal to the interior and opposite <emph>EFG</emph>: which is impossible. [<ref target="elem.1.16" targOrder="U">I. 16</ref>]</p>
       <p>Therefore <emph>AB</emph>, <emph>CD</emph> when produced will not meet in the direction of <emph>B</emph>, <emph>D</emph>.</p>
       <p>Similarly it can be proved that neither will they meet <emph>A</emph>, <emph>C</emph>. </p>
       <p>But straight lines which do not meet in either direction are parallel; [<ref target="elem.1.def.23" targOrder="U">Def. 23</ref>] <hi rend="center">therefore <emph>AB</emph> is parallel to <emph>CD</emph>.</hi></p>
       <p>Therefore etc.</p>
      </div4>
      <div4 type="QED">
       <p>Q. E. D.</p>
      </div4>
      <note n="1. falling on two straight lines," type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p><foreign lang="greek">εὶς δύο εὐθείας ἐμπίπτουσα</foreign>, the phrase being the same as that used in <ref target="elem.1.post.5" targOrder="U">Post. 5</ref>, meaning a <emph>transversal</emph>.</p>
      </note>
      <note n="2. the alternate angles," type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p><foreign lang="greek">αἱ ἐναλλὰξ γωνίαι</foreign>. Proclus (<xref n="Proc. p. 357, 9" from="ROOT" to="DITTO" targOrder="U">p. 357, 9</xref>) explains that Euclid uses the word <emph>alternate</emph> (or, more exactly, <emph>alternately</emph>, <foreign lang="greek">ἐναλλάξ</foreign>) in two connexions, (1) of a certain transformation of a proportion, as in Book V. and the arithmetical Books, (2) as here, of certain of the angles formed by parallels with a straight line crossing them. <title>Alternate</title> angles are, according to Euclid as interpreted by Proclus, those which are not on the same side of the transversal, and are not adjacent, but are separated by the transversal, both being within the parallels but one <quote>above</quote>
 and the other <quote>below.</quote>
 The meaning is natural enough if we imagine the four internal angles to be taken in cyclic order and <emph>alternate</emph> angles to be any two of them not successive but separated by one angle of the four.</p>
      </note>
      <note n="9. in the direction of B, D or towards A, C," type="crit" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
       <p>literally <quote>towards the <emph>parts B</emph>, <emph>D</emph> or towards <emph>A</emph>, <emph>C</emph>,</quote>
 <foreign lang="greek">ἐπὶ τὰ Β, Δ μέρη ἢ ἐπὶ τὰ Α Γ</foreign>.</p>
      </note>
     </div3>
     
