<div3 id="elem.10.64" n="64" type="propositions 48&#x2014;84">
      <head>PROPOSITION 64.</head>
      <p><hi rend="ital">The square on the side of a rational plus a medial area applied to a rational straight line produces as breadth the fifth binomial</hi>. </p>
      <p>Let <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> be the side of a rational plus a medial area, divided into its straight lines at <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, so that <hi rend="ital">AC</hi> is the greater; let a rational straight line <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> be set out, and let there be applied to <hi rend="ital">DE</hi> the parallelogram <hi rend="ital">DF</hi> equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">AB</hi>, producing <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> as its breadth; I say that <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> is a fifth binomial straight line. </p>
      <p>Let the same construction as before be made. </p>
      <p>Since then <hi rend="ital">AB</hi> is the side of a rational plus a medial area, divided at <hi rend="ital">C</hi>, therefore <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> are straight lines incommensurable in square which make the sum of the squares on them medial, but the rectangle contained by them rational. [<ref target="elem.10.40" targOrder="U">X. 40</ref>] </p>
      <p>Since then the sum of the squares on <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi> is medial, therefore <hi rend="ital">DL</hi> is medial, so that <hi rend="ital">DM</hi> is rational and incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.22" targOrder="U">X. 22</ref>] </p>
      <p>Again, since twice the rectangle <hi rend="ital">AC</hi>, <hi rend="ital">CB</hi>, that is <hi rend="ital">MF</hi>, is rational, therefore <hi rend="ital">MG</hi> is rational and commensurable with <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.20" targOrder="U">X. 20</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">DM</hi> is incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">MG</hi>; [<ref target="elem.10.13" targOrder="U">X. 13</ref>] therefore <hi rend="ital">DM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MG</hi> are rational straight lines commensurable in square only; therefore <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> is binomial. [<ref target="elem.10.36" targOrder="U">X. 36</ref>] </p>
      <p>I say next that it is also a fifth binomial straight line. </p>
      <p>For it can be proved similarly that the rectangle <hi rend="ital">DK</hi>, <hi rend="ital">KM</hi> is equal to the square on <hi rend="ital">MN</hi>, and that <hi rend="ital">DK</hi> is incommensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">KM</hi>; therefore the square on <hi rend="ital">DM</hi> is greater than the square on <hi rend="ital">MG</hi> by the square on a straight line incommensurable with <hi rend="ital">DM</hi>. [<ref target="elem.10.18" targOrder="U">X. 18</ref>] </p>
      <p>And <hi rend="ital">DM</hi>, <hi rend="ital">MG</hi> are commensurable in square only, and the less, <hi rend="ital">MG</hi>, is commensurable in length with <hi rend="ital">DE</hi>. </p>
      <p>Therefore <hi rend="ital">DG</hi> is a fifth binomial. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
