<div3 id="elem.5.22" n="22" type="proposition">
      <head>PROPOSITION 22.</head>
      <p><emph>If there be any number of magnitudes whatever</emph>, <emph>and others equal to them in multitude</emph>, <emph>which taken two and two together are in the same ratio</emph>, <emph>they will also be in the same ratio</emph> ex aequali. </p>
      <p>Let there be any number of magnitudes <emph>A</emph>, <emph>B</emph>, <emph>C</emph>, and others <emph>D</emph>, <emph>E</emph>, <emph>F</emph> equal to them in multitude, which taken two and two together are in the same ratio, so that, <hi rend="center">as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, so is <emph>D</emph> to <emph>E</emph>,</hi> and, as <emph>B</emph> is to <emph>C</emph>, so is <emph>E</emph> to <emph>F</emph>; I say that they will also be in the same ratio <emph>ex aequali</emph>, <hi rend="center">&lt;that is, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>C</emph>, so is <emph>D</emph> to <emph>F</emph>&gt;.</hi>
       </p>
      <p>For of <emph>A</emph>, <emph>D</emph> let equimultiples <emph>G</emph>, <emph>H</emph> be taken, and of <emph>B</emph>, <emph>E</emph> other, chance, equimultiples <emph>K</emph>, <emph>L</emph>; and, further, of <emph>C</emph>, <emph>F</emph> other, chance, equimultiples <emph>M</emph>, <emph>N</emph>. </p>
      <p>Then, since, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>B</emph>, so is <emph>D</emph> to <emph>E</emph>, and of <emph>A</emph>, <emph>D</emph> equimultiples <emph>G</emph>, <emph>H</emph> have been taken, and of <emph>B</emph>, <emph>E</emph> other, chance, equimultiples <emph>K</emph>, <emph>L</emph>, <hi rend="center">therefore, as <emph>G</emph> is to <emph>K</emph>, so is <emph>H</emph> to <emph>L</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.4" targOrder="U">V. 4</ref>]</hi>
      </p>
      <p>For the same reason also, <hi rend="center">as <emph>K</emph> is to <emph>M</emph>, so is <emph>L</emph> to <emph>N</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Since, then, there are three magnitudes <emph>G</emph>, <emph>K</emph>, <emph>M</emph>, and others <emph>H</emph>, <emph>L</emph>, <emph>N</emph> equal to them in multitude, which taken two and two together are in the same ratio, therefore, <foreign lang="la">ex aequali</foreign>, if <emph>G</emph> is in excess of <emph>M</emph>, <emph>H</emph> is also in excess of <emph>N</emph>; if equal, equal; and if less, less. [<ref target="elem.5.20" targOrder="U">V. 20</ref>] </p>
      <p>And <emph>G</emph>, <emph>H</emph> are equimultiples of <emph>A</emph>, <emph>D</emph>, <hi rend="center">and <emph>M</emph>, <emph>N</emph> other, chance, equimultiples of <emph>C</emph>, <emph>F</emph>.</hi>
      </p>
      <p>Therefore, as <emph>A</emph> is to <emph>C</emph>, so is <emph>D</emph> to <emph>F</emph>. [<ref target="elem.5.def.5" targOrder="U">V. Def. 5</ref>] </p>
      <p>Therefore etc. Q. E. D.</p>
     </div3>
     
